(
"ai_sub_version": "3.6.0",
"generated_at": "2026-10-08T00:10:29.842828",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"service_tier": null,
"service_tier_subtitles": null,
"service_tier_lyrics": null,
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
のっちゃ！
Nochya!
あらら？メラメラ、あちちメラ！
Oh? Blazing, sizzling hot!
ホロライブアソビまわり隊、ご利益担当のピキョ！シーサランダー！
The fortune-bringing Pikyo Shisalandar of Hololive's Asobi Mawari-tai!
あちちメラメラの、のっちゃ！
Blazing hot, nochya!
本日2回行動ですのっちゃ！
This is my second stream today, nochya!
のっちゃ。
Nochya.
おぬしらは、いかがお過ごしじゃろうか？
How are you all doing today?
のじゃばんわー！
Nojabanwa!
のじゃばんわー
Nojabanwa~
朝も見た気がする？
You feel like you saw me this morning too?
朝に引き続き、夜も一緒に過ごしてくれて嬉しいのじゃ。
I'm happy that you're spending the evening with me too, following this morning.
ん？今日お休み？お仕事から帰ってきたところ？お仕事お疲れ様なのじゃ。
Hmm? Are you off today? Or did you just get back from work? Good work today!
初見のじゃ？初見のじゃ、やったのじゃ！
Is this your first time seeing me? Yay, a newcomer!
秋葉原でスタートデッキ予約した？あ！わしのスタートデッキ、あちちメラデッキ予約してくれたの？ありがとうなのじゃ。
Pre-ordered the starter deck in Akihabara? Ah! You pre-ordered my Achichi-Mera Deck? Thank you so much!
映画見てた？いい日なのじゃ。
You were watching a movie? That's a good day.
しごおきたく？やっぱお仕事の...
Shigoo-kitaku? I guess...
民が多い。「インフルだから毎日見れる」？安静にするのじゃ、インフルの時は。横になるのじゃ。
...there are a lot of people from work. "I have the flu, so I can watch you every day"? Rest well when you have the flu. Lie down!
うん。
Yeah.
先輩のライブ帰り？ライブお疲れ様なのじゃ。楽しかった？
On your way back from a senior's live concert? Thanks for going! Was it fun?
うん、うん。
Mm-hmm.
グッズ頼んだ？グッズ、やったのじゃ！ありがとうなのじゃ。
You ordered merchandise? Yay, merch! Thank you so much!
ふん、ふん、ふん。「テスト勉強しながら見てる」？
I see, I see. "I'm watching while studying for a test"?
勉強になるかの？勉強になるか分からんけれど、
I wonder if this will help you study? I don't know if it will, but...
わしの配信を見て捗るといいな。捗りますように。
I hope watching my stream helps you make progress. I hope it goes well.
うん、うん、うん。
Mm-hmm.
アーカイブ見てた？やったのじゃ、ありがとうなのじゃ！
You were watching the archives? Yay, thank you so much!
秋葉原のかくれんぼ、まだやってるの？
Is the Akihabara hide-and-seek still going on?
まだ、あ！なんか、お店に、なんか、わしたちの、のぼりとかが置いてくれてるみたいの...
It's still... Oh! Apparently, there are banners of us set up in stores...
の見たのじゃ。
...which I saw.
「レベル999の村人」？え！わしが知ってるやつかな？あれおもろいよね。
"The Level 999 Villager"? Ah, is that the one I know? That's really fun, isn't it?
たぶん知ってる。読んだことある気がするのじゃ。
I think I know it. I feel like I've read it before.
うん。
Yeah.
「ミームの勉強になるかも」？確かに、今日の配信、ミームの勉強になるかも知れない。
"This might help me learn memes"? True, today's stream might be good for learning memes.
ふん、ふん、ふん。
I see, I see.
「朝のは寝坊したからアーカイブで見た」？え、嬉しいのじゃ！ありがとうなのじゃ。
"I overslept this morning, so I watched the archive"? Oh, I'm so happy! Thank you!
なんか、リアルタイムで見るよりさ、アーカイブで見る方がハードルが高いと思ってて、
I feel like watching archives has a higher hurdle than watching in real-time,
じゃから嬉しいのじゃ、ありがとうなのじゃ。
so that makes me really happy. Thank you so much!
「もれ」？「もれの事」って何か？
"More"? What is "more-no-koto"?
ちょっと待って。なんかルンバが動き始めた音した。
Wait a second. I think I heard the Roomba start moving.
なんか、あの、女の人の声聞こえたらルンバじゃから、気にし、いや、切ってくるか。
If you hear a woman's voice, that's just the Roomba. So don't worry—actually, let me turn it off.
ちょ、ちょっ、ちょっと待つのじゃ。
Wa- Wa- Wait just a moment.
ちょっと待つのじゃ。
Wait just a moment.
ルンバが動き始めた。
The Roomba has started moving.
待たれよ。
Hold on.
ちょっと何しとるんじゃ、お前。
Hey, what are you doing?
何しとるんじゃ！
What do you think you're doing?!
おるっ。
Hey!
よいしょ、よいしょ、よいしょ。よいしょ、よいしょ。のじゃ。
Heave-ho, heave-ho... Alright.
のじゃー！
Noja!
閉じ込めてきた。
I locked it away.
閉じ込めてきたのじゃ。
ルンバ...
The Roomba...
ルンバが喋り始めてびっくりした。
It startled me when the Roomba started talking.
なんか、あの
It's just, like...
走ってる最中に充電が切れて
it ran out of battery while it was running,
充電が切れて、充電が多分完了して
and after it finished charging,
再度走り直して
it started running again.
あの、走り出す音がしたから、ちょっと、うん、籠に
I heard it start up, so... yeah, I put it back in its cage.
籠に入れてきた。ルンバに名前はつけてない。
I put it in its cage. I haven't named my Roomba yet.
何つけようかな。
I wonder what I should name it.
うん。
Yeah.
そう、でも、配信中じゃとうるさいからね。
Right, but it's too noisy during streams.
うるさいから、あの、どかしてきたのじゃ。うん、働こうとしてた。
Since it's noisy, I moved it away. Yeah, it was trying to work.
のじゃ。
Noja.
さて。
Now then.
今日やるゲーム、おぬしら
Have you guys
見たことある？
ever seen the game we're playing today?
今日は、「手垢の付いたことしか言わない彼女」っていうゲームで
Today, we're going to play a game called "Teaka no Tsuita Koto shika Iwanai Kanojo"
遊んでいこうと思うんじゃが、思うんじゃが、
(The Girlfriend Who Only Says Clichés),
どういうゲームかというか、あの
and as for what kind of game it is...
何だろう、恋愛ゲーム？
How should I put it, a dating game?
恋愛シミュレーションゲームって言うんじゃろうか？ギャルゲ的な
Or maybe a dating sim? Like a bishoujo game,
感じで、なんか選択肢を選べる系のゲームっぽくて、
where you choose options.
なんじゃが、あの、普通のゲームはさ、
But, in normal games,
ただ女の子を攻略するじゃん？攻略する感じだと思うんじゃが、
you just romance the girls, right? That's usually the goal.
あの、今回、ノベルゲーム？それじゃ、ノベルゲーム。
But this time... a visual novel? Yes, a visual novel.
うん。
Yeah.
なんじゃが、あの、なんと、今回登場する女の子のキャラが、
But surprisingly, the female character in this game
インターネットで擦り切った、浅いネタしか喋らないらしくて、
only speaks in shallow internet memes.
そう。
Yes.
そうそう。
Exactly.
ギャルゲやったことないのじゃ。ちなみに、なんか、あの、
I've never played a bishoujo game. By the way,
ノベルゲーム的なのは多分初見。
this is probably my first time playing a visual novel too.
やったことない気がするのじゃ。あるんかの？
I don't think I've ever played one. Have I?
多分、記憶にある限りない気がする。初めての、
As far as I can remember, I haven't. My first time
初めての女の子攻略が、あの、ネットに
romancing a girl will be with one who only speaks
救いたい？
You want to save?
過去の自分を救いたいのじゃ。
I want to save my past self.
過去の自分と向き合って、救って、全部受け入れる。
Confronting my past self, saving them, and accepting everything...
配信に…
...in this stream...
したいのじゃ。うん。
...is what I want to do. Yes.
のじゃ。
Indeed.
いや、ちょっと心が苦しいけど。
My heart aches a little, but...
心が苦しいけど。
My heart aches, but...
やっていこうと思いますのじゃ。
...I've decided I'll go ahead with it.
さすがに女の子とのデートでお面つけてるのは失礼かな？
"Is it rude to wear a mask on a date with a girl?"
で、デート？
A-A date?
デートって。
A date...
やっぱ。
I guess...
お顔全部見せたほうがいいのかな？
...I should show my whole face?
どうじゃろ？
What do you think?
超失礼？
Is it super rude?
外したほうがいい？
Should I take it off?
どう、どう思う？
What, what do you think?
おしゃれ？おしゃれかも！おしゃれかもよ、確かに。
Stylish? Maybe it's stylish! It might indeed be stylish.
ミステリアスでいい？失礼？
"Mysterious is fine"? Or is it rude?
落とせるかな？これで。
Can I win her over with this?
不審者？
"Suspicious person"?
え、でも不審者だけど、横に女の子いたら許される説ない？
But even if you look suspicious, isn't there a theory that it's allowed if a girl is with you?
もし一人だったら不審者じゃけど。
If I were alone, I'd definitely be suspicious, but...
なんか横に女の子がいるだけで、なんか大体許される感じある。
...just having a girl next to me makes it feel like it's mostly allowed.
「マッチアップのデートなんてマスクしてるからええ」？
"People wear masks for matchmaking app dates anyway, so it's fine"?
そんなもんなのじゃ？
Is that how it is?
人間のデートはマスクしてるもんなのじゃ？
Do humans wear masks on dates?
「不審者は否定しない」？じゃって。
"You won't deny the suspicious person part"? Well...
髪から炎でてたら不審者じゃろとは思うから、あんま否定できないのじゃ。
...if someone has fire coming out of their hair, they're suspicious anyway, so I can't really deny it.
え、おぬしらわしの可愛いお顔見たい？
What, do you guys want to see my cute face?
可愛いお顔見たい？
Do you want to see my cute face?
見たい？
Do you?
見せてほしい？
Do you want me to show you?
「自分はどっちでもいい」。
"I'm fine either way."
のじゃ。
Indeed.
見たいって言ってほしいのじゃ。
I want you to say you want to see it.
見たい人がいっぱい！見せてあげますのじゃ！
There are so many people who want to see it! I shall show you!
じゃ、お部屋移動するから。
Well, I'm switching scenes, so...
おぬしら高評価を押して、待っててほしいのじゃ！
...I want you all to hit the like button and wait!
いくのじゃ！
Here I go!
ん？どうやって外す？ほっ！
Hmm? How do I take it off? Hop!
遅かった。遅かったのじゃ。
Too slow. I was too slow.
よし、それじゃ、BGMをつけますのじゃ。
Alright, then, let me turn on the BGM.
よいしょ。
There we go.
音量どうかの？
How is the volume?
おっきいかの？
Is it too loud?
おっきい、ちっちゃいがあったら教えてほしいのじゃ。
Let me know if it's too loud or too quiet.
ちょっとおっきいかな？
Maybe a bit too loud?
「この画面からすでにキツい」？
"The screen is already painful to look at"?
そんな！
No way!
いい感じ？多分良い。ちょうど良い。
Is it good? Probably good. Just right.
よし。途中でなんか気づいたら教えてほしいのじゃ。
Alright. If you notice anything during the stream, let me know.
はい、こちらが今回の…今回の配信。
Yes, this is today's... today's stream.
てあカノ。 手垢のついたことしか言わない彼女。
"Teakano: The Girl Who Only Speaks in Cliches."
インターネットで擦られきったアサイーミームしか喋らない。
She only speaks in overused internet memes,
彼女っぽいんじゃが。
...it seems.
「インフルエンザのときの夢みたいですね」
"It's like a dream you have when you have the flu."
この顔で？この顔で？この顔で？
With this face? With this face? With this face?
ちょっと、なんかドキドキさせそうなさ。
It's kind of like she's trying to make your heart skip a beat,
ねえ、距離感もきっと近くてさ。
...and the physical distance must be close too,
近いさ、距離近くてドキドキするシチュエーションでさ。
...and in a heart-fluttering situation where you're close together,
ね、私「〇〇君のこと気になってるみたいです」みたいなさ。
...she'd go, "It seems like I'm interested in you, XX-kun,"
顔をしながらさ。
...making that face, and then...
インフルエンザのときの夢みたいですね。
"It's like a dream you have when you have the flu."
ハート？！
With a heart emoji?!
A heart?!
このセリフでハート？！
With that line?!
なんじゃ？何が起きたらこのセリフが？日常生活であんまこのセリフ出てくることなくない？
What? What could possibly trigger this line? This doesn't really come up in daily life, does it?
ていうか、あんまり日常生活でミーム言う機会ない気がするのじゃ。
In fact, I don't think there are many opportunities to use internet memes in daily life.
よくわかんない。そんなミームあった？
I don't really get it. Was there a meme like that?
ミームというか、わりとネットで擦られきった表現ではないかの？
Rather than a meme, isn't it more of an overused phrase on the internet?
インフルエンザのときの夢みたい。
"Like a dream you have when you have the flu."
ネットで擦られきった表現を多用してくれる子らしい。
Apparently, she's a girl who frequently uses worn-out internet expressions.
言わない？わし聞いたことあるよ。「インフルエンザのときの夢みたいですね」みたいな。
She doesn't? I've definitely heard it before, like "It's like a dream you have when you have the flu."
「Twitterのノリで話してくる人」？
"Someone who talks with the vibe of Twitter"?
なんか、あの、関係値の薄いネットのフォロワーとオフ会した時ってこんな感じ。
It's like... when you meet up in real life with an internet follower you barely know.
なんか、ネットのさ、あの、いいねとか送り合うぐらいのさ。
Like, with an internet friend where you only exchange likes,
あんま会話したことない、「おはよう」リプとかしかさ、やり取りしないフォロワーとさ。
...who you barely talk to, except maybe replying "good morning,"
会ったときさ、話すこと本当に本当になくてさ。
...when you meet them in person, you have absolutely nothing to talk about,
話すこと本当に本当になくて、こういうことしか言えない。
...absolutely nothing to talk about, so you can only say stuff like this.
ネットミームのことしか言えないのじゃ。
She can only say internet memes, then.
そんな人と会うな。確かに。
"Don't meet someone like that!" True.
お主らインターネット防災訓練受け直すのじゃ。そんな関係値の浅い人と会っちゃダメなのじゃ。
You guys need to retake your internet safety training. You shouldn't meet someone you barely know.
確かに。確かに。
True. True.
話すことない人と会うなー！確かに。
Don't meet up with someone you have nothing to talk about with! True.
メラちゃんの1on1が怖くなってきた。いや、
"Mera's 1-on-1 is getting scary." No,
1on1する頃にはさすがにお主らの間に思い出ができるじゃろ。
by the time we do a 1-on-1, we'll surely have some memories together.
思い出が皆無のフォロワーと会った時にこういう会話が発生するんじゃよ。
This kind of conversation happens when you meet a follower you have zero memories with.
ってことはさ、この女の子とさ、あの、俺君？俺君？僕？なんじゃろ。
Which means, this girl and... who is it, "Ore-kun"? "Ore-kun"? Or "Boku"?
主人公もしかしてあんまり関係値が育まれてないのでは？
Maybe the protagonist hasn't really built up a relationship with her yet?
てかそうじゃない？インターネットミームでさ、
Actually, isn't that it? That they can only converse
しか会話できないってさ、結構関係値なくない？
using internet memes suggests they don't really have a relationship.
結構関係値ないのにもかかわらず、デート？
Even though they barely have a relationship, they're going on a date?
なんじゃ？何をしていらっしゃる？
What is this? What are they doing?
何をしていらっしゃるか。え、彼女って書いてるけど、付き合ってるのかな？
What on earth are they doing? It says "girlfriend," so are they dating?
付き合ってこのセリフ？「ですね…」だって。
Dating and she says this? "I guess..." she says.
ま、でも、あれか。付き合っても敬語キャラはいるか。
Well, I guess there are polite-speech characters even after dating.
お互い距離感誤ってそうなカップル、確かに。
"A couple that seems to have gotten their distance wrong." True.
じゃ、俺君も彼女ちゃんも両方とも、
So both Ore-kun and Kanojo-chan
インターネットではよく喋るけど、リアルだとあんまり喋れない…
talk a lot on the internet, but in real life, they can't talk much—
やめてほしいのじゃ！そんなこと言わないでほしいのじゃ！
Stop it! Please don't say that!
傷つきますのじゃさすがに！さすがに傷つきますのじゃ！のじゃのじゃのじゃ。
That hurts! That seriously hurts! Noja, noja, noja...
ふー、ふー。
Fuu... Fuu...
これって、わしのことだ。
This is about me...
これって、わしのことだ。もう帰りたい。もう帰りたい。
This is about me. I want to go home. I want to go home.
もう帰りたいのじゃ。
I want to go home...
もう帰るボタンない？まだない？まだ帰るボタンがない。
Isn't there a "go home" button? Not yet? There isn't one yet.
「まだ付き合いたて」確かに。
"They just started dating." True.
ほやほやのね。付き合いたてほやほやでこんなこと言っていいんか？
Freshly started, huh? Is it okay to say this when they've just started dating?
耐えれるかのう。
Will I be able to endure this?
よし、じゃあ。始めていきますか。
Alright then. Shall we get started?
最初から。よし。
From the beginning. Alright.
プレイヤー名を入力。
Input player name.
何にしよっかな。め、メラとかにする？メラ。
What should I name him? Me... "Mera"? Mera.
メラ。
Mera.
のじゃ、のじゃ君とかでもいいけど。一旦、メラか。
Or maybe "Noja-kun"? Let's go with Mera for now.
メラお？メラおにするか。
Merao? Should I name him Merao?
やっぱ、わし男の子じゃからな。メラおにするか。
After all, I'm playing a boy. Merao it is.
メラおいくか。
Let's go with Merao.
わし、メラお。メラおいくのじゃ。
I am Merao. I'll use Merao.
オッケー。メラおなのじゃ。
Okay. Merao it is.
一人称を選んでください。俺、僕、私、自分、ウチ、自分の名前。
"Please select a first-person pronoun: Ore, Boku, Watashi, Jibun, Uchi, Own Name."
ああ、わしがない。ねえ、わしがない、わし。わしがない。
Ah, there's no "Washi". Hey, there's no "Washi". No "Washi".
自分の名前かな？一人称メラおでいくのじゃ。
Maybe "Own Name"? My pronoun will be Merao.
メラおでいかせていただこうと思うのじゃ。
I'll go with Merao.
さすがにわしはないか。
As expected, there is no "Washi".
この年齢の中高生とかかな？
Middle or high schoolers of this age?
高校生とかの女の子とお付き合い、わしがお付き合いしたらまずいか。
Dating a high school girl... is it bad if I date her?
わし415歳じゃから、
Since I'm 415 years old,
一体400歳が未成年とデート、やばいか？
is a 400-year-old dating a minor bad?
やばいか？のじゃ。おけのじゃ。
Is it bad? Noja. Okay, noja.
それでは、行きますのじゃ。オッケー。
Well then, let's go. Okay.
一人称メラおもきつい？そんな！
"Using Merao as a pronoun is tough too." No way!
あ、始まりましたのじゃ。
Oh, it has started.
シチュエーションは駅。駅で待ち合わせしてる感じかな？よいしょ。
The situation is a station. They are meeting up at the station, I guess? Up we go.
メラお「栗志江さん、まだ来てないな」栗志江ってなんで栗志江なんじゃ？
Merao: "Cliché-san isn't here yet." Cliché? Why is her name Cliché?
くり、し、え。
Cli, ché.
なんかこういう系の名前ってさ、わりと由来あるじゃん。
You know, names like this usually have some kind of origin.
クリーシェ。クリーシェって何？
Cliché. What is cliché?
クリーシェって何？わし知らない。
What is cliché? I don't know.
わしそれの元ネタ知らない。
I don't know the origin of that.
フランス語で使い古された言い回しのこと。なるほど。
"A overused phrase in French." I see.
栗志江モカさん。使い古されたクリーシェの、クリーシェっぽい。
Cliché Moka-san. Overused cliché, very cliché-like.
栗志江モカさん。メラおと同じ1年A組のクラスメイト。
Cliché Moka-san. A classmate from Class 1-A, same as Merao.
成績優秀で、可憐で、物腰も穏やか。入学式時点で「いいよね……」と話題になっていた。
"Excellent grades, lovely, and gentle. People talked about her at the entrance ceremony, saying 'She's great...'"
あ、いいよね。高嶺の花的なね。高嶺の花的な。
Ah, "She's great." Like a prize beyond reach. Like a prize beyond reach.
お顔も可愛いしね。髪もロングで清楚そう。
She has a cute face, too. Long hair, looking neat and tidy.
1学期が始まって2週間。なかなか話しかけるタイミングがなかったけど……
"Two weeks since the first term started. I barely had a chance to talk to her, but..."
映画に誘ったら、なんとOKをもらえた。
"when I invited her to the movies, she actually said yes!"
ちょいちょいちょい、メラお、距離感！距離感なのじゃ！
Whoa, whoa, whoa, Merao, your distance! Pay attention to the distance!
今日を機に仲良くなれたらいいな！
"I hope we can get closer starting today!"
でも、メラおさ、こういう子じゃよ。なんか高嶺のさ、花のさ、高嶺の花のさ、
But you know Merao, he's that kind of guy. Some unreachable girl, like a prize beyond reach...
ね、栗志江さん、いいなって思って、
Merao thought Kurishie-san was nice,
関係値特にないのに映画に誘う、この、距離感。
so despite not really being close, he invites her to a movie. This distance...
コミュニケーションの距離感のバグり方。
This glitch in communication distance!
オタク君さ、でも、こうしないと、あの、事態というのは発展しませんね。
Mr. Otaku, but if he doesn't do this, the situation won't progress, will it?
うん、発展しないから、グイグイ。
Yeah, it won't progress, so he has to be pushy.
メラお、チャラ男なの一ちょっと嫌なのじゃ。メラお、チャラ男なのじゃ。
I don't really like how flirtatious Merao is. Merao is such a playboy.
何の映画見るんじゃろ。
I wonder what movie they're going to watch.
「にしても……」
[Merao: "Even so..."]
なんかめっちゃきもい。何この、あの、色が、
It looks so gross. What is this... color?
すごい、まがまがしい色。
It's like, so sinister.
なんか、平成のお土産コーナーとかに、いた。
It feels like something you'd find in a Heisei-era souvenir corner.
平成の女子高生がカバンにこぞってつけてたような、色味と、奇妙さ。
The kind of weirdness and color scheme that Heisei high school girls would all hang on their bags.
なんじゃこれ。ピカソか？ゲーミングピカソか？
What is this? Is it Picasso? Gaming Picasso?
なんじゃこれ、現代アートか？
What on earth is this? Modern art?
ま、こういうのがね、意外と、なんか、うん千万とかするからな。
Well, things like this actually end up costing tens of millions of yen sometimes.
ちいかわではないのじゃ。ちいかわではないのじゃ、間違いなく。なんじゃこれ。
It's definitely not Chiikawa. Definitely not Chiikawa. What is this?
「改札前のオブジェ。何なんだろう。待ち合わせ場所にはいいけど」
[Merao: "An object in front of the ticket gate. What is it? It's good for a meeting spot..."]
確かに、こんだけね、こんだけ目立ったらね。
True, if it stands out this much.
これ何て呼ぶんだろう。改札前で待ち合わせする時さ、まるまる前で待ち合わせねって言われるけどさ、これ何て名付けられるんじゃろうな。
I wonder what people call this. Like when meeting in front of a ticket gate, they'd say "Let's meet in front of [blank]", but how would this be named?
「（このオブジェ、何というか……）」
[Merao: "(This object, how should I say...)"]
何というか何？
How should you say what?!
「（…………いや、やめとこ）」
[Merao: "(...No, never mind)"]
え、もしかして、これがインフルエンザの時の夢？
Wait, could this be "a dream you have when you have the flu"?
なーにこれ、何なのじゃ、何なのじゃこれ。
What is this? What on earth is this?
「メラおさん、おはようございます！」
[Moka: "Merao-san, good morning!"]
栗志江ちゃん来た！栗志江ちゃん来たのじゃ！メラおなのだ。
Kurishie-chan is here! Kurishie-chan has arrived! It's Merao.
「おはよう（栗志江さん！　私服だ！）_」
[Merao: "Good morning (Kurishie-san! She's in casual clothes!)"]
確かに、いつも制服しか見ないのにね、私服だとね、新鮮でかわいいの。
Indeed, we usually only see her in uniform. Seeing her in casual clothes is fresh and cute!
「よかった……やっとたどり着いた。ごめんなさい、時間ギリギリで」
[Moka: "Thank goodness... I finally made it. I'm sorry, I'm just barely on time."]
「電車遅れてた？」
[Merao: "Was the train delayed?"]
「いえ、駅の中で迷っていました」
[Moka: "No, I got lost inside the station."]
確かに。駅ってね、知らない駅とかじゃとね、広くてね、迷っちゃうよね。
True, if it's a station you don't know, it's so big that you get lost.
「都会の駅って、迷宮みたいじゃないですか？」
[Moka: "Don't city stations feel like labyrinths?"]
あ、これも確かにネットでよく聞く。あの、新宿駅とかね、渋谷駅とかね、迷路だよね。
Ah, I definitely hear that a lot online. Like Shinjuku Station or Shibuya Station. They're mazes, right?
そう、渋谷駅から出られない。そうそうそうそう。
Yeah, you can't get out of Shibuya Station. Exactly, exactly.
「わかるー」
[Merao: "I get it."]
「でも『これ』は遠くからでもすぐ見つけられました！」
[Moka: "But I could spot this easily even from far away!"]
「これ」。出たのじゃ、「これ」。出たのじゃ「これ」
"This". There it is, "this". There it is.
「何というか……まるで……」
[Moka: "How should I put it... It's almost like..."]
「『インフルエンザの時の夢』みたいですね……」
[Moka: "...a dream you have when you have the flu, isn't it?"]
きゅぴーんじゃねえよ！
Don't give me that spark sound effect!
きゅぴーん。
Sparkle~
きゅぴーんって言ったのじゃ。話す時きゅぴーんって言ったのじゃ。
She made a sparkle sound. She literally sparkled when she talked!
これがインフルエンザの時の夢？！
This is a dream you have when you have the flu?!
え、実際どう？実際どう？
Wait, what is it really like? What is it really like?
インフルエンザの時の夢ってさ、もっと空間じゃない？固形物じゃなくない？
Aren't dreams when you have the flu more about space? It's not a solid object, right?
インフルエンザの時に見る夢ってさ、こういう、なんかその、すごいいグラデーションの色のさ、サイケデリックな色のさ、空間にいない？
When you have the flu, don't you dream of being in a space with crazy gradients, psychedelic colors?
「栗志江さんと楽しく１日を過ごしましょう！」
[Game Info: Let's spend a fun day with Kurishie-san!]
「ただし、右上に『帰る』ボタンが表示されている間、プレイヤーはいつでも『帰る』ことができます。帰りたくなったらボタンを押してください。」あ、帰れるんだね。
"However, while the 'Go Home' button is displayed, you can go home at any time. If you want to go home, please press the button." Ah, you can go home.
「１日は４つのチャプターに分かれており、どのチャプターで帰るかで、５エンドに分岐します。」ほう、なるほど。ほう。
"One day is divided into 4 chapters, and depending on which chapter you go home in, it branches into 5 endings." Oh, I see. Oh.
「通常の選択肢でエンディングは変わらないので好きなものをお選びください。」あ、選択肢は何でもいいっぽいのじゃ。帰るタイミングで分岐がある系。
"The endings don't change based on regular choices, so please choose whatever you like." Ah, so any choice is fine. The branching depends on when you decide to go home.
「インフルエンザの時の夢……」
[Merao: "A dream you have when you have the flu..."]
もう帰れるのじゃら。もう帰れるよ。もう帰れるよ。どうする？もういいか？
We can already go home, you know. We can already go home. What should we do? Should we wrap it up?
一旦価値観の違いで帰るか？
Should we go home first due to a "difference in values"?
あの、インフルエンザの時の夢は絶対に固形じゃないのじゃ。映画は行く、確かに。確かに確かに。映画とかは行くか。ま、可愛いしな。可愛い女の子が変なこと言っててもギリ許せるしな。
I mean, a dream when you have the flu is definitely not a solid object. But we'll go to the movie, true. True, true, let's go. Well, she is cute. If a cute girl says something weird, you can barely let it slide.
「（さっきメラおが思いとどまったことを……）」
[Merao: "(Exactly what I held myself back from saying earlier...)"]
お前も思ったんかい！メラおも思ったらしいのじゃ。メラおも思ってるなら、まあ、
You thought so too?! Apparently, Merao thought so too. Well, if Merao thought so too, then...
相性がいいのか？
Are they compatible?
うん、メラおとクリシエさんはどうかはさておき、メラおはね
Hmm, leaving aside how Melao and Crisier-san are, Melao...
思ってるっぽいから、お似合いなんじゃ、お似合いカップルなんじゃ
seems to think so, so aren't they a good match? Aren't they a matching couple?
高熱の時って、複雑で変なものが夢に出てきたりしませんか？
When you have a high fever, don't complicated, strange things appear in your dreams?
なんでドヤ顔なんだよ！
Why that smug face!
なんで、なんでお前はそのドヤ顔になれるんだよ！
Why, why can you make that smug face!
自信満々なのじゃ。ま、まあ可愛いか。
She's so full of confidence. W-well, is it cute?
まあ、可愛い女の子がわけ分からんこと言ってたら可愛いか。
Well, if a cute girl says things that don't make sense, is that cute?
もしかして……比喩として斬新すぎたでしょうか？
Could it be... that was too novel as a metaphor?
この子斬新すぎたと思ってる！インフルエンザの時の夢でドヤって
This girl thinks it was too novel! Getting smug about a dream during the flu...
斬新すぎたと思ってる！ちょっと可愛い。
...and she thinks it was too novel! That's a bit cute.
ちょっと可愛いな。斬新すぎたでしょうか。
A bit cute. "Could it be too novel?"
え、どっちがいいんだ？『そうかも』。
Eh, which is better? "Maybe so".
『そうかも』で、褒め？『そうかも』が褒めなのじゃ？
With "Maybe so", is it a compliment? Is "Maybe so" a compliment?
『そんなことないよ』はディス？
Is "Not at all" a diss?
でも『そんなことないよ』の方が共感？どっちだ？『そうかも』の方が
But is "Not at all" more empathetic? Which one? Will "Maybe so"
好感度上がるか？一旦『そうかも』か。
increase affection more? Let's go with "Maybe so" first.
言われてみれば珍しい例えかもね
Come to think of it, that might be an unusual metaphor.
高熱の時に変わった夢を見る人はあまりいないのでしょうか……？
Are there not many people who see strange dreams when they have a high fever...?
いる。いる。わしも見るよ。わしも変な夢見る。
Yes. Yes. I see them too. I see strange dreams.
でもわし大体炎上する夢。わしの悪夢大体炎上する夢なのじゃ！
But for me, they are usually dreams where I get flamed. My nightmares are mostly dreams where I get flamed!
とか、なんか、あの、自分の意識がないまま、あの、なんか、良くないことツイートしちゃって
Or like, having no control over myself, tweeting something bad...
ツイ消しできない夢とか。んー、そういう夢なのじゃ。
and not being able to delete the tweet, dreams like that. Yeah, dreams like that.
んー、避難訓練できてない夢。結構怖い夢見るのじゃ。うーん。
Yeah, dreams where I'm not prepared for evacuation. I see pretty scary dreams. Hmm.
空気悪い……、別の話しないと！
The atmosphere is bad... I have to change the subject!
のじゃ。ま、まだ時間あるしスタバ行く？
Indeed. "W-We still have time, want to go to Starbucks?"
あーデートっぽい。デートっぽい！映画までの間にスタバ。うん、うん、うん。
Ah, that's like a date. Like a date! Starbucks before the movie. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
新作はチョコミントだって！あー、そういうシーズンあるよね。のじゃ。
"The new flavor is mint chocolate chip!" Ah, there is that season. Indeed.
スタバ！？あの……！
Starbucks!? Um...!
てかなんかさ、このクリシエさんさ、所作がお嬢様っぽいからさ、
I mean, this Crisier-san, her behavior is so ladylike,
あんまスタバとか行ったことなさそう。お嬢様キャラっぽくない？歯磨き粉来るかな？
she doesn't seem like she goes to Starbucks often. Doesn't she seem like an ojou-sama? Will "toothpaste" come up?
どうせ歯磨き粉とか言うんじゃろう？
She's probably going to call it toothpaste, right?
絶対歯磨き粉って言う！読めてきた、この、この子の思考。
She will definitely say toothpaste! I can read her, her way of thinking.
スタバって、注文が呪文みたいなやつですよね！？
Starbucks is the place where the order sounds like a magic spell, right!?
これ冷笑だろ！これ冷笑じゃろ！なんか、なんかさ、いや、分かるよ。
This is cynicism! This is cynicism, isn't it! Like, well, I get it.
わしもね、わしもね、人間、てか人間の、人間の中学生時代にね、スタバ冷笑してた時期あったけどね。
I also... I mean, when I was in human junior high school, I had a phase where I sneered at Starbucks.
冷笑してた時のキメ台詞が、あれでしょう、注文が呪文みたいなやつじゃろだからね。
The signature phrase when sneering at it is "the orders are like magic spells, right?"
は、あ、ああーもう、もう！もう、恥ずかしい！
Ah, geez, already! Geez, so embarrassing!
いや、嫌な記憶。嫌な記憶。
No, unpleasant memories. Unpleasant memories.
なんかクラスメイトが、なんかスタバに行くとかさ、そういうイベントがあって。
Like, my classmates going to Starbucks, they had an event like that.
わし誘ってもらえなくて、それが悲しくて冷笑してたのじゃ。
I wasn't invited, and because I was sad, I sneered at it.
誘ってもらえないのが悲しくて、『ああ、あのなんか呪文みたいなやつじゃろ』みたいな。ああー！
Being sad about not being invited, saying things like "Oh, that place with the spell-like orders, right." Aahhh!
帰っていい？帰っていいのじゃ？ちょっと、つら、つら、つらくなってきた。
Can I go home? Can I go home? I'm getting a bit... it's getting painful.
つらくなってきたのじゃーー！
It's getting painful!
いや、耐える。耐える耐える耐える。ちょっ、一旦、一旦最後まで見るか。
No, I'll endure. Endure, endure, endure. L-let's just watch to the end first.
あと、個人的な価値観ですけど、チョコミントって歯磨き粉みたいでちょっと……
Also, this is just my personal value, but mint chocolate chip is a bit like toothpaste...
出たーーー！そういうこと言っちゃう。そういうこと言っちゃう。
There it is! Saying things like that. She went and said it.
わしチョコミント、わりと好きじゃけど。苦手ではない。苦手ではないけど。
I actually quite like mint chocolate chip. I don't dislike it. I don't dislike it, but...
これさ、モカちゃんさ、クラシエさんさ、あのメラお君がさ、チョコミント大好物のチョコミント者だったらどうしてたん？
What if Melao-kun was a mint-choco fan whose favorite food is mint chocolate?
火種じゃよ、これ。これ火種。これ火種なのじゃ。炎上するのじゃ。
This is a spark. This is a spark. It could start a fire. It's going to get flamed.
配信者がこれ言ったら、あの、場合によっては、ご時世によっては、燃える可能性のあるセリフですのじゃ。まあでも、一般、一般高校生じゃからね。うん。のじゃ。
If a streamer says this, depending on the situation or the times, it's a line that could cause them to get flamed. Well, but she's just a normal high school student, after all. Yeah. Indeed.
注文はメラおがするよ！チョコミント以外にも色々あるし！
Melao will do the ordering! There are many other flavors besides mint chocolate!
あ、メラお出来る男。フォロー、フォロー、フォロー。
Ah, Melao is a capable guy. Follow-up, follow-up, follow-up.
ありがとうございます。注文までしていただいて……メラおさんって、とっても優しいんですね！
Thank you very much. Having you even do the ordering... Melao-san, you are very kind!
あ、好感度上がった！なんか好感度上がった！
Ah, affection went up! Somehow affection went up!
なんか上がった！やったー！
Something went up! Yay!
あはは……気にしないで。
Ahaha... Don't worry about it.
黒志江さんって、こんな感じなんだ。
So Kuroshie is like this.
なんか……
I mean...
見た目的には、もっとお嬢様系清楚おっとり系だと思ったけど、
Based on her looks, I thought she'd be more of a refined, quiet, gentle type,
意外と俗っぽいな。
but she's surprisingly down-to-earth.
意外と俗っぽいお嬢ちゃん。
A surprisingly down-to-earth girl.
（話題は振ってくれるけど……ちょっと聞いたことある話が多いな）
(She brings up topics, but... a lot of them are things I've heard before.)
いいだろ、別に！
Who cares?
めらお、お前それ望みすぎじゃ！それは望みすぎなのじゃ！
Merao, you're asking for way too much! That's way too much!
いいじゃろ、別に！聞いたことある話しても！
Who cares if it's something you've heard before?
可愛い女の子が話したらなんでも、お前……
If a cute girl is talking, no matter what it is, you...
お前、VTuberの配信でも「その話前も聞いた」とか言うタイプ？！
Are you the type to say "I've heard that story before" during a VTuber stream too?!
許せねえのじゃ！めらお！
Unforgivable! Merao!
めらおが許せねえから帰るのじゃ！
Since I can't forgive Merao, I'm going home!
めらおが許せねえのじゃ！
I just can't forgive Merao!
のじゃー！ゆる、許してよ……許してほしいのじゃ……のじゃー……
Noja! P-Please forgive me... I want you to forgive me... Noja...
でも、知ってる、知ってる話さ、「あ、僕もそれ知ってるよ」とかさ、ねえ。
But still, if it's a story you know, you can say, "Oh, I know about that too." You know?
あ、アンガーマネジメント。1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 のじゃ……
Oh, anger management. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, noja...
ふうー……よし。
*Sigh*... Okay.
（気を使って、話題をたくさん出してくれてるのかも）
(Maybe she's trying to be considerate and bring up lots of topics.)
そうじゃよ！そうじゃよ！初めてのデートでおデート！
Exactly! Exactly! It's your first date, a real date!
1対1だよ！クラスメイトとさ、1対1でさ、大して仲良くなくてさ。
It's one-on-one! One-on-one with a classmate you're not even that close with.
大して仲良くない相手とさ、デートに行ってさ、話す内容がないんだよ！めらお、お前と話すことがねえのじゃ！
When you go on a date with someone you aren't close with, you run out of things to say! Merao, she has nothing to talk about with you!
お前と話すことがねえのに、黒志江さんはすごい気を使って話してくれてるのに、お前望みすぎなのじゃ！
She has nothing to talk about with you, yet Kuroshie-san is being so considerate and talking to you, but you're asking for way too much!
うん。
Yeah.
そろそろ出よう。
Let's head out.
うわ、暑……っ！
Wow, it's hot...!
いや、令和はね、温度差がね、やばいのじゃ。
Seriously, the temperature shifts in the Reiwa era are crazy.
まだ4月なのに……。
Even though it's only April...
「最近暑すぎたり、急に寒くなったり、季節感がおかしい気がします」
"It's been too hot lately, and then suddenly cold. I feel like the seasons are acting weird."
いや、これはね、ガチ。これはガチなのじゃ。
Yeah, this is so true. This is absolutely true.
令和ちゃんがね。あ、これはわし、またつまんない、わしが、わしが、わしがそれなのじゃ。
Reiwa-chan, you know. Ah, wait, this is me being boring again. I'm, I'm, I'm the one doing that.
令和ちゃんとか言っちゃダメ？
Am I not supposed to say "Reiwa-chan"?
うわー！同じこと考えてるのじゃーー！
Whoa! She's thinking the exact same thing!
「令和には、もっと頑張ってほしいですよね……」
"I really wish Reiwa would try a bit harder..."
のじゃーー！わし同類？
Nojaaa! Am I just like her?
わし、わし、わし、もう例証対象？
Am I, am I, am I already the object of illustration?
わしが悪い？擦られきったことしか言えない同類なのじゃ？
Is it my fault? Am I just like her, only able to say overused jokes?
のじゃ……
Noja...
（その話題7回くらいした気がする）
(I feel like we've had this conversation about seven times already.)
いや、毎年してるのじゃ。のじゃ……わし……
Well, we do say it every year. Noja... Am I...
わし、もしかしてインターネットで擦られきった浅い話しかできない系VTuberなのじゃ？
Am I, by any chance, a VTuber who can only tell shallow, overused internet jokes?
のじゃー！
Noja!
（そんな話をしていると、あっという間に映画館についた）
(As we chatted about things like that, we arrived at the movie theater in no time.)
もう結構ダメージが……もう結構ダメージが……のじゃ。
I've taken quite a bit of damage already... Quite a bit of damage... Noja.
「ラブコメホラーアクションでしたっけ？映画、楽しみです！」
"Was it a romantic comedy horror action? I'm looking forward to the movie!"
ラブコメホラーアクション見るらしい。結構もりもりなのじゃ。
Looks like they're watching a rom-com horror action. It's packed with genres.
本当にホラー、平気なんだよね？
You're really okay with horror, right?
ホラー見るらしい。わし、ホラーダメ。
Apparently they're watching horror. I can't stand horror.
ね、わしホラーダメ。わしホラーダメ。
Yeah, I'm bad with horror. I'm bad with horror.
でもめらおはいけるらしい。
But Merao seems to be fine with it.
犬猫が死なないかは見ておきたいけど……
I'd like to check if any dogs or cats die in it, though...
確かに、女の子とデートに行って、犬猫が死ぬあの内容だったら割と空気が、空気が終わってしまうのじゃ。
True, if you go on a date with a girl and a dog or cat dies, the atmosphere would completely, completely die.
「はい。最近ホラーにハマってるので。任せてください！」
"Yes! I've been really into horror lately, so leave it to me!"
あ、黒志江さんホラーにハマってるらしい。
Oh, Kuroshie-san is apparently into horror.
ならよかった。
That's good then.
「他にも映画、色々ありますね。あのポスターとか」
"There are lots of other movies too. Like that poster over there."
いっぱいポスターがあるらしい。リバイバル上映だね。
Looks like there are a lot of posters. A revival screening.
昔の映画を劇場でやるみたい。リバイバル上映って言うらしいよ。
They show old movies in theaters. Apparently it's called a revival screening.
リバイバル上映多いよね。
There are a lot of revival screenings, aren't there?
「そういうのもあるんですね！あの映画は？」
"Oh, they do those too! What about that movie?"
平成アニメのリメイクだよ。
It's a remake of a Heisei-era anime.
リメイク多くね？
There are so many remakes.
平成アニメのリブートだよ。
It's a reboot of a Heisei-era anime.
「あれは？」
"And that one?"
「昭和名作特撮が復活！」だって。
It says, "The revival of a Showa-era masterpiece tokusatsu!"
全部同じことなのじゃ。でもまあ、確かに。流行ったものをやるのは王道なのじゃ。
They're all basically the same thing. But well, true. Doing what was popular is the classic way.
「今って、本当に令和なんですか？！」
"Is it really the Reiwa era right now?!"
確かに。このラインナップだったらそうなるかも。
True. With this lineup, you'd definitely wonder.
（黒志江さんが困惑している）
(Kuroshie looks bewildered.)
上映後……。
After the movie...
（よかったな。何かのパロっぽいシーン多かったし、あとで解説見よう）
(That was good. There were a lot of parody-like scenes, so I'll look up some explanations later.)
なんかパロディっぽいシーン多くてもさ、パロディ元が分かんなくてさ、
Even if there are many parody-like scenes, you might not know the reference,
結局なんかそのさ、映画のさ、ハッシュタグとかでさ、解説してくれてる人とかを見るよね。
so in the end, you look at the movie's hashtag and check out people who explain it, right?
メチャメチャ見るのじゃ。見まくっちゃうのじゃ。
I look at them a lot. I end up looking at them like crazy.
栗志江さんはどうかな？
How about Kurishie-san?
面白かった〜！！ めらおさんはどうでした！？ 楽しかったですか？
That was so fun! How about you, Merao-san? Did you enjoy it?
あ、うん……自分の感想？
Ah, yeah... My own thoughts?
そうだね……ええと……
Let's see... Well...
映画の感想って言うの難しくない？
Isn't it hard to give your thoughts on a movie?
難しくない？
Isn't it?
感想って、結構、高度な技術な気がしますのじゃ。
I feel like giving your thoughts requires a high level of skill.
それより、栗志江さんの感想が聞きたいな！
More than that, I want to hear Kurishie-san's thoughts!
あーもう、どうせ、どうせなんかパロディの話するんでしょ？ どうせパロディの話なのじゃ。
Ah, jeez, she's probably going to talk about parodies, right? It's bound to be about parodies.
はい！ 怖くて面白かったです！ 色々あったけど、最後は助かってよかったです！
Yes! It was scary and interesting! A lot happened, but I'm glad they were saved in the end!
うん。なんか、普通、いい、普通の事。当たり障りない事。うん。なんじゃ。
Yeah. Like, normal, good, normal things. Harmless things. Yeah. What is it?
特に、敵のボスがとっても怖かったですね。
Particularly, the enemy boss was very scary.
わ、分かった！ねぇ、私何て言うか分かった！ねぇ、私何て言うか分かった！
Ah, I know! Hey, I know what she's going to say! Hey, I know what she's going to say!
どうせさ、怖いってさ、……ちょ、一旦見るか。一旦見るか。
She's probably... Wait, let's watch for a second. Let's watch for a second.
どうせさ、本当に怖いのは、とか言うんじゃろ？
She's probably going to say "What's truly scary is...", right?
あー、部下を裏切って殺してた人。
Ah, the person who betrayed and killed their subordinates.
この映画、モンスターも怖いけど――
In this movie, the monsters are scary, but...
どうせさ、本当に怖いのは人間なのかもしれませんね、とか言うんじゃろ？
She's probably going to say "What's truly scary might be humans," right?
怖いけど？ 来るぞ、来るぞ！
Scary, but? Here it comes, here it comes!
本当に怖いのは、人間なのかもしれませんね……
What's truly scary might be humans...
500回見たのじゃ！ 500回見たのじゃ！
I've seen this 500 times! I've seen this 500 times!
確かに、ちょっと気持ちよくなってきた。ここまで当てられると、ちょっと気持ちよくなってくるのじゃ。
Indeed, this is starting to feel a bit good. When I get it right to this extent, it feels a bit good.
なるほど。なるほど。本当に怖いのは、人間なのかもしれ……
I see, I see. "What's truly scary might be humans..."
なんかさ、あの、私ネタツイ見るの好きなんじゃけどさ、ネタツイでよくあるじゃん。
You know, I like looking at meme tweets, and you see this a lot on meme tweets.
カスの〇〇、カスの〇〇。本当に怖いのは、人間なのかもしれませんね、とか。
"Trashy [Title], trashy [Title]. What's truly scary might be humans," or...
〇〇は私たちの心の中にいるのかもしれませんね、みたいな。
"[Title] might be inside our hearts," or something like that.
ネタツイで500回見る、あの言われ方ね。
That's the phrasing you see 500 times in meme tweets.
のじゃ。一言のじゃ。
Indeed. Exactly.
う、うん。
Y-Yeah.
それと……知ってますか？
Also... did you know?
映画で「やったか！？」という台詞が出たら、大抵生きてるんですよ。
In movies, when someone says "Did we get him?!", they're usually alive.
そうじゃ。「やったか？」って言ったら、大抵生きてるのじゃ。
Exactly. If they say "Did we get him?", they're usually alive.
正しいのじゃ。お主は正しいのじゃ。ね、可愛くなってきた。
You're right. You're totally right. Hey, she's starting to become cute.
なんか可愛いわ。孫を見守る気持ち。
Somehow, she's cute. It's like watching over a grandchild.
なんか、インターネット初心者を見守る気持ちですのじゃ。
It's like watching over an internet beginner.
ここまで来ると可愛らしいのじゃ。帰るとかじゃない。
At this point, it's just endearing. It's not about going home anymore.
可愛いのじゃ。ドヤ顔でね、やった。やったかを言っちゃダメなのじゃ。
She's just cute. Doing it with a smug face. You can't say "Did we get him?".
そ、そうなんだ。
I-I see.
ご飯どうする？
What should we do about food?
よ、よければ、このお店にしませんか？
I-If you'd like, how about this place?
栗志江さんは、スマホを開いてマップを見せてきた。
Kurishie-san opened her smartphone and showed me a map.
カメダ珈琲店か、いいね。
Kameda Coffee Shop, huh? Nice.
ね、私分かった！ね、分かったこれ何て言うか！
Hey, I know! I know what she's going to say!
絶対デカすぎって言うのじゃ！もう！
She's definitely going to say "It's too big!" Jeez!
はい！ では、これから向かいましょう！
Yes! Let's head there now!
もうーー！ 500回聞いたのじゃ！
Jeez! I've heard that 500 times!
2名様どうぞ〜
Two people, right this way.
栗志江さん、カメダ好きなの？
Kurishie-san, do you like Kameda?
はい、大好きです！
Yes, I love it!
いいよねー、落ち着くし。
It's great, very relaxing.
知ってましたか？カメダ珈琲の料理って、メニューの写真より実物の方が量、すごいんですよ……？
Did you know? The food at Kameda Coffee actually has a much bigger portion size in reality than in the menu photos...?
５億回見たのじゃ。５億回聞いたのじゃ。
I've seen it 500 million times. I've heard it 500 million times.
逆写真詐欺。逆写真詐欺のじゃ。
Reverse picture fraud. It's reverse picture fraud!
そうじゃな。実際でかいよね。実際でかい。え、でも何か、キツくないな？思ったよりキツくないな？
That's right. It really is huge. Really huge. But wait, it's not that bad, is it? It's not as tough as I thought.
何か可愛らしい。ネット初心者と共にデートしてる。うん。
It's somehow cute. Like dating an internet beginner. Yeah.
可愛いんじゃない？後追い感すごい、ネット流行の。確かに。かなり後追いなのじゃ。
Isn't it cute? Her grasp of internet trends is way behind. True. She's completely behind the times.
しかも、豆菓子も付いてくるんです……！
And they even give you bean snacks...!
あれうまいよね。あの豆めっちゃうまいのじゃ。
Those are delicious, aren't they? Those beans are so good.
わしあの豆めっちゃ好き。
I really love those beans.
友達がいらないって言ったら、あ、友達がいらないって言ったのをもらってね、食べる。しょっぱくてうまいのじゃ。うん。
If my friend says they don't want them, I take what they didn't want and eat them. They're salty and delicious. Yeah.
確かに、魅力的だよね。
Indeed, it's appealing.
（カメダのパンケーキ美味しそう。菓子メーカーとコラボしてるんだ）
(Kameda's pancakes look delicious. They're collaborating with a snack maker.)
カメダよくコラボしてるよね、お菓子のメーカーとかと。色んなとことコラボしてるの見るのじゃ。うん。
Kameda often collaborates, doesn't it? With snack makers and such. I often see them collaborating with various places. Yeah.
（あーっ）終わった！
(Ah!) It's over!
終わった！終わったのじゃ！帰る、帰る、帰る、帰る！
It's over! It's over! Let's go home, go home, go home, go home!
今日、今日の朝の、Duolingo配信で、今日の朝のDuolingo配信で、
Today, this morning, during my Duolingo stream... in this morning's Duolingo stream,
あのコメント欄に放火魔が来て、コメント欄に放火魔が来て、
a flamer came to the chat, a flamer came to the comments,
どっち派か聞かれたのじゃ。どっち派か聞かれまして。
and asked which side I was on. I was asked which side I was on.
あの、あの炎上が怖すぎて、あえて答えませんでしたのじゃ。うむ。
I was too scared of getting flamed, so I purposely didn't answer. Yup.
ちょっと、怖くて。ちょっとそんな責任、わし負えなくて。怖かったから答えなかったのに。
I was a bit scared. I couldn't take on that kind of responsibility. I didn't answer because I was scared, but...
来る、来やがれ、お前！なんちゅうこと！
it's coming! Damn you! What is this?!
配信してんだぞ、今！今配信してんだぞ、わし！答えは沈黙！
I'm streaming right now! I'm streaming right now, you know! My answer is silence!
はあ、落ち着いて、落ち着いて、落ち着いて。のじゃ。うん。あ。
Sigh, calm down, calm down, calm down... noja. Yeah. Ah.
……めらおさん。
...Melaou-san.
（来ちゃった）
(She came.)
え、これ好感度めっちゃ下がるんじゃない？これ好感度バカ下がるのじゃ。
Wait, isn't this going to tank my affection meter? This will insanely lower her affection.
いや、答えは沈黙ですのじゃ。うん。
No, the answer is silence! Yeah.
私たち、まだ関係は浅いですが……立場を明確にすることも大切ですよね。
Our relationship is still brief, but... it's also important to make our stances clear, isn't it?
終わった。終わったのじゃ。絶対、絶対選択肢で来る！
I'm finished. I'm doomed. It's definitely, definitely going to give me a choice!
終わったのじゃ。のじゃあ。
I'm finished! Nojaa.
その……今後、より親密な関係になるために……めらおさんはどっち派ですか？
Um... in order for us to become closer in the future... which side is Melaou-san on?
きのこと、たけのこの……
Between Kinoko and Takenoko...
うわ、選択肢出てる！
Whoa, the choices popped up!
ううわあ。
Uuugh.
配信してますのじゃ。配信中配信中（配信中）ですのじゃ。
I'm streaming right now. I'm currently on stream.
沈黙なし？スキップとか、スキップとか？
No option for silence? What about skipping? Can I skip?
ちょ、一旦帰るか？
Wait, should I just go home for now?
（きのこたけのこのノリに巻き込まれるのはごめんだよ！）
(No way I'm getting dragged into the Kinoko-Takenoko war!)
ヴーッ、ヴーッ。あ、母さん、何の用？え……今日だっけ？うん、わかった。
*Buzz, buzz* Ah, Mom, what is it? Eh... was that today? Yeah, got it.
ごめん！家の用事があって帰らないといけなくなった。
Sorry! Something came up at home, so I have to go back.
……それは仕方ないですね。今日はお開きにしましょう。
...That can't be helped, then. Let's call it a day today.
うん、ごめんね。
Yeah, sorry.
（一か八か、口でバイブレーションしたけど何とかバレなかったな）口でバイブレーションしたんかい！したけど何とかバレなかったな。
(As a last resort, I vibrated with my mouth, but somehow she didn't realize.) You vibrated with your mouth?! "but somehow she didn't realize"...
戦略的撤退のじゃ、撤退のじゃ！
It's a strategic retreat! A retreat!
え、これ、全、全ルート回収無理じゃね？
Wait, isn't it impossible to complete all routes like this?
（やっぱり、昨日は悪いことをした。会ったら嘘ついたの、謝ろう）
(As I thought, I did a bad thing yesterday. I'll apologize for lying when I see her.)
あ……
Ah...
栗志江さん！おはよう。
Kurishima-san! Good morning.
お、おはようございます。
G-Good morning.
ええと……き、今日も暑いね。
Um... It-It's hot today as well, isn't it?
はい！本当に……あ、ちょっと、すみません。
Yes! Really... Ah, excuse me for a second.
うん？
Hm?
（栗志江さん、スマホを操作して何か確認してる）
(Kurishima-san is looking at her phone to check something.)
すみません。やっぱり何でもないです。
Sorry. It's actually nothing.
何か言おうとしてなかった？
Weren't you trying to say something?
天気デッキ使おうとしてた。
She was trying to use the weather card (deck).
いいえ、気にしないでください。
No, please don't worry about it.
（栗志江さんは何かを言う前に、スマホで調べるようになった）
(Kurishie-san started checking on her smartphone before saying anything.)
え、何？何調べてるの？何調べてるの？
Eh, what? What is she looking up? What is she looking up?
（きっと……自分の言葉が言い尽くされた表現かどうか確認してるんだろう）
(Surely... she is checking if her words are cliché expressions.)
え、切なくてワロタ。切ないのじゃ。なんか喋れなくなっちゃった。心配なのじゃ。
Eh, that's sad, lol. It's sad. She can't talk anymore. I'm worried.
（……何故かそうだ、わかった）
(...For some reason, I understood.)
（自分も、似たようなものだからだ）
(Because I am similar.)
ED3「教えてAI」
Ending 3 "Teach me, AI"
エンディング3のじゃー！
Ending 3!
なんかエンディング切なかったのじゃ。
Somehow, the ending was sad.
え、なんか、わしが途中で帰っちゃったから？
Eh, is it because I went home in the middle?
わしが途中で帰っちゃったから？
Because I went home in the middle?
続きからしたらさ、続きから行けるかな？
If I choose "Continue", can I go from where I left off?
保存されてるデータがない。行けないっぽい。
There's no saved data. It seems I can't.
ちょっとじゃあ、あの、思っているより切ない系じゃったから、
Well then, since it's sadder than I thought,
あの、腹を括ってきのこたけのこ戦争に参加しますのじゃ。
I'll steel myself and participate in the Mushroom-Bamboo Shoot War.
参加させていただきますのじゃ。
I will participate.
セーブ、セーブしなきゃいけないの？
Do I have to save?
できそうだった？ちょっと見るか。
Was it possible? Let's check.
チャプター選択。
Chapter Select.
あ、いけた！
Ah, it worked!
店員：2名様どうぞ〜
Clerk: Table for two, please.
いけたっぽい！よし。
It worked! Nice.
栗志江さん、カメダ好きなの？
Kurishie-san, do you like Kameda?
はい、大好きです！
Yes, I love it!
いいよねー、落ち着くし。
It's nice, very relaxing.
……知ってましたか？カメダ珈琲の料理って、メニューの写真より実物の方が量、すごいんですよ……？
...Did you know? Kameda Coffee's dishes are actually served in much larger portions than shown in the menu...?
しかも、豆菓子も付いてくるんです……！
And they even come with a side of bean snacks...!
確かに、魅力的だよね。
That's certainly appealing.
（カメダのパンケーキ美味しそう。お菓子メーカーとコラボしてるんだ）
(The Kameda pancakes look delicious. They're collaborating with a snack manufacturer.)
来るぞ、来るぞ！わしは、ちょっと炎上はごめんですのじゃ。
It's coming, it's coming! I'd rather avoid getting flamed.
炎上はごめんですのじゃ。お主ら、お主らいい？あのね、わしはね、
I don't want to get flamed. Everyone, are you ready? You see,
巻き込まれたくない！
I don't want to get involved!
お主らに任せるのじゃ。
I'll leave it to you all.
これはね、わしの選択ではない。
This is not my choice.
民意なのじゃ。
It's the will of the people.
民意ですのじゃ。
The will of the people!
これによって、他責なのじゃ！
Therefore, it's others' responsibility!
他責にするのじゃ！
I'll pass the buck!
これでわしは燃えない。
This way, I won't get burned.
嫌なのじゃ。なんか、たけのこが優勢じゃの。
I don't like it... somehow, Bamboo Shoots are in the lead.
きのこ37の、たけのこ63。
Mushrooms 37, Bamboo Shoots 63.
いよし、いよし。神回避ですのじゃ。
Alright, alright. A god-tier evasion!
……めらおさん……
...Merao-san...
（来ちゃった）
(It's here...)
私たち、まだ関係は浅いですが……立場を明確にすることも大切ですよね……
Our relationship is still new, but... it's important to make our stances clear, right?
その……今後、より親密な関係になるために……めらおさんはどっち派ですか？
In order for us... to become closer in the future... which side are you on, Merao-san?
きのこの、たけのこの……
Mushrooms, or Bamboo Shoots...?
はい！コメント欄の！
Yes! It's the comment section's!
コメント欄の選択なのじゃ！
It's the comment section's choice!
わしじゃないのじゃ。わしの選択じゃないよ！
It's not me. It's not my choice!
ちょ、一応証拠も見せる？
Should I show the evidence just in case?
一応証拠も見せるか。一応証拠も見せるか。
Shall I show the evidence? Let's show the evidence just in case.
一応証拠も見せるか。証拠ですのじゃ！
Let's show the evidence. Here's the proof!
わしの選択じゃないよ！
It's not my choice!
たけのこが選ばれましたのじゃ。わしじゃないよ！
Bamboo Shoots have been chosen. It's not me!
やはり他責こそ正義。のじゃー！
As expected, shifting blame is the ultimate justice! Yeah!
たけのこだよ。
"It's Bamboo Shoots."
ガーン
Shock!
お！栗志江さん、きのこ派か？
Oh! Is Kurishie-san on the Mushroom side?
こ、これからも……お友達でいてくれますか……？
C-Can we still... be friends...?
そこまでじゃないよ！縁切るレベルじゃないよ！
It's not that serious! It's not a deal-breaker!
やばい、栗志江さん、きのこ派だったっぽい。
Oh no, Kurishie-san seemed to be on the Mushroom side.
きのこ派だったっぽい。好感度下がったのじゃ。
She seemed to be on the Mushroom side. Her affection level dropped.
好感度下がっちゃったのじゃ。帰らねえのじゃ。
Her affection level dropped. I won't go home.
さっき帰ったら悲しそうだった。悲しませたくないのじゃ。
She looked sad when I left earlier. I don't want to make her sad.
栗志江さん、わかってると思うけど。正直はっきり言うのもあれだけど……
Kurishie-san, I think you know this, but to be honest, it's awkward to say it clearly, but...
きのこたけのこ論争って、ごっこ遊びだから。本気じゃないよ。
the Mushroom-Bamboo Shoot debate is just a make-believe game. It's not serious.
そうなんですか？
Is that so?
「アレ」を何て呼ぶか、みたいなもんだよ
It's like what you call 'that' thing.
あー！もう！
Ah! Geez!
あ、そうやって
Ah, like that...
配信してるんじゃが！
I'm streaming right now!
どうする？これでさ、メラおちゃんがこれ派だったからって、ちょっともうメラおちゃんちょっと信じられないな、みたいになったらどうすんの？
What if my viewers are like, "I can't believe Merao-chan is on that side," and stop trusting me? What will we do?
どうしてくれるのじゃ？
What are you going to do about it?
「あれを何て呼ぶかみたいなもんだよ」
"It's like what you call that snack."
うわあ。
Whoa.
もう「任意」にするか。ちょっと「任意」とさせていただくのじゃ。
I'll just choose "Optional." Let's make it "Optional."
そう、しかもこれ地方によるし、地域バレしちゃう。
Yeah, plus it depends on the region, so it might reveal my location.
地域バレの危険がありますのじゃ。ちょっと「任意」とさせていただきますのじゃ。
There is a risk of revealing my location. So, I will go with "Optional."
すみません。それは、何でしょうか。
I'm sorry. What is that?
丸い生地で中身はあんこの、たい焼きの円盤バージョンみたいなお菓子。
A round pastry with red bean paste inside, like a disc-shaped version of taiyaki.
うーん。やっぱり、わからないです。
Hmm. I still don't know.
（……薄々思ってたけど、世間知らず？ いや、世間知らずっていうか――）
(...I had a feeling, but is she sheltered? Or rather...)
アイスコーヒー、メロンソーダ、エビカツサンドとフライドチキンセット、ハムサンドサラダセットです！
Here is your iced coffee, melon soda, shrimp cutlet sandwich with fried chicken set, and ham sandwich salad set!
おお、多くね？二人で食べる量なのじゃ？これが健康的な男女デートの量なのじゃ？多いのじゃ。
Whoa, isn't that too much? Is that a portion for two? Is this what a healthy date portion looks like? It's a lot.
わあ、いただきます！
Wow, thank you for the food!
いただきます。
Thank you for the food.
（黒志江さんはメロンソーダにエビカツサンド、フライドチキンセットをもりもり食べていた）おお、だいぶ食べる。
(Kuroshie-san was heartily eating her shrimp cutlet sandwich, fried chicken set, and melon soda.) Oh, she eats quite a lot.
いっぱい食べる子、可愛いのじゃ。
Girls who eat a lot are cute.
（見た目からは想像できないくらい、健啖家なんだなあ……）
(I wouldn't have guessed from her appearance that she has such a hearty appetite...)
いっぱい食べたのじゃ。
She ate a lot.
うん。
Yeah.
公園に移動した。
We moved to the park.
（カフェでお腹がパンパンになったので、公園に散歩に来た）公園に来たのじゃ。うん。
(Since our stomachs are stuffed from the cafe, we came to the park for a walk.) We're at the park now. Yep.
（満腹すぎて、身体がにぶい。しばらく公園でゆっくりしよう）うん。
(I ate too much and my body feels heavy. Let's relax in the park for a while.) Yep.
わあ、魚がたくさん！
Wow, so many fish!
魚がたくさん。
So many fish.
カラフルできれい……
They're colorful and pretty...
カラフル。魚がカラフルなタイプに、公園にね、いるのか、のじゃ。
Colorful. The fish in this park are the colorful type, huh?
魚好きなの？今日、水族館でもよかったね。確かに、デートと言えばね、水族館みたいなところありますね。
Do you like fish? We could've gone to an aquarium today. True, speaking of dates, aquariums are a classic.
うーん、好きと言えば好きなんですけど……
Hmm, I do like them, but...
水族館の魚って、見てるとお腹が減ってきちゃ……
Looking at fish in an aquarium makes me hungry...
おねーさん！コイかいてるからどいて！
Hey, lady! We're drawing carp, so move out of the way!
あ、ガキんちょ。ドパワッパたち。ドパワッパーズ。
Ah, brats. Those kids. The bratty kids.
ま、でも、実際水族館で魚見るとお腹減っちゃうは言うよね。わしも言いたくなる。わしも言いたくなるのじゃ。
Well, but actually, people do say they get hungry when looking at fish at an aquarium. I feel like saying that too. I'd feel like saying it too.
ドパワッパーズ来たよ。
The bratty kids are here.
あ、ごめんね。
Ah, sorry about that.
（小学生たちがクーピーで絵を描いている。宿題かな）あ、クーピーでお絵描き。
(Some elementary schoolers are drawing with Coupy-pens. Is it homework?) Ah, drawing with Coupy-pens.
お絵描き？
Drawing?
うん。オレはカモ、かく！
Yeah. I'm drawing a duck!
カモ描いてるのじゃ。
He's drawing a duck.
わたしはお花！
I'm drawing flowers!
あたし、セイレーン！セイレーンいるのじゃ？この公園、セイレーンいるタイプの公園なのじゃ？
I'm drawing a siren! A siren? Is this the kind of park where sirens appear?
なるほど。
I see.
てかクーピーなんだな、クレヨンとかじゃなくて。
By the way, they're using Coupy-pens, not crayons.
へえー。
Oh.
ねえ！え、かく？かみとクーピーかしたげる！
Hey! Are you going to draw? I'll lend you some paper and Coupy-pens!
え、なんか、絵を描かせてくれるらしい。絵を描かせてくれるらしい。
Oh, looks like they're letting me draw. They're letting me draw.
……メラおが？
...Merao?
かいてかいてー！
Draw, draw!
何書く？
What should I draw?
何か「おもしろい」ものかいてよ！ちょっと、フリやばくない？
Draw something funny! Hey, isn't that a tough request?
最近の、最近のドパワッパたちのフリやばくない？おもしろいもの描いてよだって。え、何がおもろいかな？
Isn't the request from these kids these days too tough? "Draw something funny," they say. What would be funny?
何がおもろいかな？え、いや、急に言われても……
What would be funny? I mean, asking me so suddenly...
キュピーン。
Flash.
期待されてる。
They're expecting something.
ね、めっちゃ期待されてる。
Yeah, she's highly expected.
（面白い絵か……。まあ、小学生にウケるのは……）
(A funny drawing... Well, what appeals to elementary schoolers is...)
ムキむきパンのヒーロー、ムキムキ猫型ロボ。あれかな？ほにゃえもんをムキムキにしたやつか……
A muscular bread hero, a muscular cat-like robot. Is it that one? Like a muscular Dorae-mon or...
ふにゃパンマンとかをムキムキにしたやつ的な？
Or a muscular Anpan-man sort of thing?
ムキムキか。ま、一旦ムキムキパン言っとくか。ムキムキにしておくか。
Muscular, huh? Well, let's go with the muscular bread one for now. Let's make it muscular.
うん。
Yeah.
はい描けたよ。ま、子供ですからね。こういうので喜んでくれるでしょう。
Here, I drew it. Well, they're kids. They should be happy with this.
ありがとー！
Thank you!
笑えよ、ガキ。ガキ、静まり返った。ワッパ、ワッパ。笑えよ。
Laugh, kids. They went completely silent. You brats, laugh.
のじゃ。
Indeed.
……え！国民的キャラクターをマッチョにする落差がおもしろいのは小学生までっしょ！お前ら！お前ら小学生じゃないんか！お前ら、お前ら小学生じゃないんか！
"...What?! Making a national character muscular for a comedic contrast is only funny to elementary schoolers!" You guys! Aren't you guys elementary schoolers?! Aren't you guys elementary schoolers?!
ワッパ。
Brats.
わっぱ
なっ
What?
え？世知辛っ！
Eh? How cynical!
な、な、ませ…、ませ…ませわっぱ過ぎんか？
A-Are they... too precocious? Aren't they too precocious?
ませ過ぎじゃない？なんじゃお前ら、ガチ。
Aren't they way too mature? Who even are you guys, seriously?
あれ！？
Huh!?
あたしたち、生まれたときからヒカキンとセイキンあびてるもん！ど、ど、わっぱ！
“We've been showered with Hikakin and Seikin since birth!” What massive brats!
ど、どっぱわっぱ！
Total little brats!
のうじゃ。
Indeed.
もう、もう、もう、可愛げがないのうじゃ。可愛げがないのうじゃ。
They really, really have no cuteness to them. No cuteness at all.
もう、駄目じゃ。日本終わった。日本終わった。
It's over. Japan is doomed. Japan is doomed.
もう勝てねえ。HIKAKINさんとSEIKINさんの動画には勝てねえよ、わしの動画じゃ。
I can't compete. My videos could never compete with Hikakin-san and Seikin-san.
もう…
Geez...
嫌な子供！
What annoying kids!
こんな笑いじゃもう満足できないよ！
“We can't be satisfied with this kind of humor!”
マジか…… / マジか、いやガチでマジかだよ。マジかなのじゃ。
“Seriously?” / Seriously? Like, seriously. Unbelievable.
あれ、栗志江さん？ / 栗志江さんどうした？栗志江さんどうした？
“Oh, Kurishie-san?” / What's wrong, Kurishie-san? What happened?
……ッ！！　ふふ……っ！ / 大笑いしてるのじゃ。大笑いしてるのじゃ。
“...*giggle*!” / She's cracking up. She's laughing so hard.
くく……フフフ……っ！　ムキムキ……ムキムキって…… / ムキッ、ムキッって…
“Hehe... muscular... she said 'muscular'...!” / 'Muscular', she said 'muscular'...
おねーさんこんなんでわらってんの！？ / ねーさんこんなんで笑ってんの？
“Are you seriously laughing at this, big sister?” / Are you really laughing at this?
ちょ、いいじゃん！栗志江さんが笑ってるんだよ！人の笑いを、人の笑いをバカにするんじゃないよ、わっぱ！
Hey, let her be! Kurishie-san is laughing! Don't make fun of how people laugh, you brats!
良くない。良くないのじゃ。ちょ、もうちょい道徳を学ぶのじゃ、お主ら。
That's not nice. It's really not nice. You guys need to learn some manners.
これで！？　あっさ～！ / これで！？あっさ〜！ / ちょ、めすわっぱなのじゃ。何言っとるん。
“This is it? That's so shallow!” / What a cheeky brat. What are you even saying?
『いっしゅうめ』じゃん！　おねーさんやばいー！ / 『いっしゅうめ』じゃん！おねーさんやばい！ / いっ、そんな酷いこと言うなよ、お前！
“She's only on her 'first lap'! She's so basic!” / Hey, don't say such mean things!
いっしゅうめって！ませてんねえ。ませてんねえ！
“First lap”? Wow, they're precocious. So mature!
いっしゅうめって！いいじゃろ！面白いものは面白い、でいいじゃろ！
Calling it a “first lap”... who cares? If it's funny, it's funny!
失礼な！！　散れ！　散れ！ / 失礼な！散れ、散れ！本当に失礼な、わっぱ。
“How rude! Go away! Go away!” / How rude. Shoo, shoo! Truly rude brats.
は～い / は〜い
“Okay~”
こういうさ、言葉遣いどこで覚えてくるの？どこで覚えてくるの、こういう言葉遣い。
Seriously, where do they learn that kind of vocabulary? Where do kids learn these words?
誰が教えた？YouTubeか？お主、YouTubeでこんなこと、誰かがいっしゅうめとか、人を笑っていた？
Who taught them? YouTube? Did they see someone on YouTube laughing at others for being on their “first lap”?
良くないものを摂取しておりますのじゃ。
They're consuming really bad content.
あまみゃの配信を見て、優しい心を学ぶのじゃ。
You should watch Amamya's streams to learn a kind heart.
……スー……はぁ……はぁ……
*deep breath* *sigh*
……ごめんなさい。変ですよね
“I'm sorry. I must seem weird.”
まあ、急にツボに入るのってよくあることだよ
“Well, suddenly getting a giggling fit happens to everyone.”
いいえ、それだけじゃなくて……　今日一日……私、変だったでしょう
“No, it's not just that... I must have seemed strange all day today, right?”
変？　そうかな
“Strange? I wouldn't say so.”
メラオさん……　ごめんなさい。今日、私のお話にここまで付き合って下さって……
“Merao-san... I'm sorry. Thank you for listening to my stories all day...”
え……？
“Eh...?”
私のお話……きっと、あまり楽しくないから。これ以上付き合っていただくのも、悪いです
“My stories aren't very fun, I'm sure. I'd feel bad keeping you any longer.”
ねえ、さっきのさ、どっぱわっぱたちがさ、酷いこと言ったせいで、モカちゃん傷ついちゃってるのじゃ！
Look, Moka-chan got hurt because of those awful little brats!
モカちゃんが、へこんじゃってるよ！ねえ！ガチ、何？何傷つけてるん、人を！
Moka-chan is totally down! Seriously, what's wrong with them? Why would they hurt her like that?
もしよろしければ、ここで解散にしませんか？ / 帰らない！絶対に帰んないのじゃ！
“If it's alright with you, shall we call it a day?” / No, we're not going home! We're absolutely not leaving!
ちょ、ここまで言われたら、女の子が悲しんでる、女の子が悲しんでる！帰らない！
Wait, seeing her so sad... we definitely can't leave her like this! Don't go home!
栗志江さん
“Kurishie-san.”
は、はい
“Y-Yes?”
ベンチで休まない？
“Would you like to rest on the bench?”
いいですけど……
“I'd like that, but...”
うー、可哀想に。こんなこといっぱい言われてきたのかな、今まで。
Aww, poor thing. I wonder if she's had to deal with mean comments like that this whole time.
栗志江さんって、中学までどんな感じだったの？
“What was your life like up until middle school, Kurishie-san?”
両親の都合で、今年３月まで欧州にいました。小中は全寮制の女子校でしたね
“Due to my parents' work, I was in Europe until this March. I went to an all-girls boarding school.”
確かに！確かにこの経歴ならね！この経歴ならね、全寮制の女子校にいたら確かに、俗っぽいインターネットに
Aha! That background makes perfect sense! If she was in an all-girls boarding school, she wouldn't have been exposed to
触れることない、隔離されてるから、知らないよねえ！
the trashy side of the internet. Since she was isolated, she has no idea!
知らないよねえ！そうじゃったらもう、全部新鮮だよねえ！
She doesn't know any of it! To her, everything is completely fresh!
じゃあもう、しゃあないじゃん。笑うなよ。笑うなよ、この子のこと。
So it can't be helped. Don't laugh at her. Stop making fun of her!
あ、帰国子女なんだ
“Ah, so you're a returnee.”
帰国子女なんだ！
A returnee!
私も！私も私も私も！
Me too! Me too, me too, me too!
和菓子にピンと来てなかったのはそういう訳か
So that's why Japanese sweets didn't ring a bell...
あの、ニイのね。ニイのあんこの入った、あの丸、丸いお菓子ね。確かに確かに。うん。
Ah, the "nii" thing. That round sweet filled with anko, right? True, true. Yeah.
前は、校則が厳しくて、TVもスマホも禁止。
Before, the school rules were strict, and TV and smartphones were banned.
娯楽はド〇えもんとア〇パンマンの本だけでした。
My only entertainment was Doraemon and Anpanman books.
でも今年、日本に帰ることになったので、父を説得して公立高校に進学したんです。
But since I was returning to Japan this year, I persuaded my father and went to a public high school.
なるほど。
I see.
やっと、やっと、日本の子供らしい人間の生活ができるようになったの？
She can finally, finally, live a human life like a Japanese kid?
できるようになったのに！
Even though she finally can...
時代かのう？冷笑されちゃってるんじゃ。
Is it just the times? She's being ridiculed.
ひどいんじゃ！ひどいんじゃ、世界って！
That's terrible! The world is so cruel!
へえ、スマホは持ってただよね。それも解禁されたの？
Oh, "You did have a smartphone. Was that unbanned too?"
はい！私、普通の学生生活が送れるようになったんです！
Yes! I'm now able to lead a normal student life!
いい話じゃん、いい話じゃん！
That's a nice story! That's a nice story!
つまんないとか言ってごめん、浅いとか言ってごめん、一周目とか言ってごめん！
Sorry for saying it's boring, sorry for saying it's shallow, sorry for saying it's the first playthrough!
やっぱ誰にでもあるからね、初めてって。
Everyone has their first time after all.
その初めての楽しさを笑うことなんてね、しちゃいけないのじゃ。
We shouldn't laugh at that initial joy.
それで春休みは行きたいお店とイベントに全部行って、映画とドラマ三昧で……！
So during spring break, I went to all the shops and events I wanted to, indulged in movies and dramas...!
この春休みは、初めて知ることがたくさんありました！
This spring break, there were so many things I learned for the first time!
いい話じゃん。
That's a nice story.
「かき氷シロップはどれも味は同じ」とか……
Like, "shaved ice syrups all taste the same"...
「結婚の予定がある新兵は死ぬ」とか……
or "new recruits planning to get married will die"...
まあ、まあそう。まあそう。
Well, well yeah. Well yeah.
実際かき氷のシロップって本当に同じなんじゃろうか。言うけどね。
Are shaved ice syrups actually the same? People say that though.
毎日新しい発見があって、楽しかった。
Every day had new discoveries, and it was fun.
ご学友の皆さんとも共有したかった。
I wanted to share them with my classmates too.
そうだよね、発見ってね、発見って共有したいよね。
True, discoveries, you want to share them.
でも……
But...
でも？
But?
新しい発見だと思ってたのは、私だけだったんです。
I was the only one who thought they were new discoveries.
切ないのじゃ……！
That's sad...!
まあ誰か日本で過ごしてね、子供の頃からYouTube見てたらね、触れてるよね。
Well, if you grew up in Japan and watched YouTube since you were a kid, you'd know them.
……そういえば、先週、隣の席で女子３人が何か言ってたな
...Come to think of it, last week, three girls in the next seats were saying something.
意地悪なこと言ったんでしょ！女子３人意地悪なこと言った？言ったんじゃろう？
They said something mean, didn't they?! Did the three girls say something mean? I bet they did!
栗志江さん、どう？
How about Kurishie?
んー……悪い子じゃないけど……つまんないかも。
Hmm... She's not a bad girl, but... she might be a bit boring.
それ！知ってる話しかしないよね！
Exactly! She only talks about things everyone already knows!
ちょ、厳しくない？お笑いに厳しくないか？女子、お笑いに厳しくないか？
Whoa, aren't they too harsh? Isn't that a bit harsh on comedy? Girls, aren't you too harsh on comedy?
そういう話は教室でするな。
Don't say things like that in the classroom.
聞こえる可能性あるとこでするな。
Don't do that where they can hear you.
この前も「スマホの充電１％は意外と持つ！」って言っててさー
The other day she said, "1% battery on smartphones surprisingly lasts long!"
いいじゃろ言ったって、１％は意外と持つよ！
So what if she said that? 1% really surprisingly lasts long!
やばｗ
Oh my god, lol.
やばじゃないのじゃ！
It's not "oh my god"!
それショートで流れてきたら飛ばすわーｗ
If that showed up in my shorts, I'd skip it lol.
のじゃー！はい、あちちメラニに500のダメージ！
No way! Okay, 500 damage to Achichi Melani!
えー、なんかやっぱ動画とか見ながらこういうこと思われてるのかな、「ショートで流れてきたら飛ばすわ」とか思われてるのじゃー！
Man, I wonder if people think that when watching videos, like "if that showed up in my shorts, I'd skip it"!
はい、ダメージ、ダメージなのじゃ。VTuber、バーチャルユーチューバーあちちメラニに500のダメージなのじゃ。
Yep, damage, total damage. 500 damage to VTuber, Virtual YouTuber Achichi Melani.
これガチ言われたら泣く、大泣くなのじゃ、大泣きですのじゃ。
If someone actually told me that, I'd cry, I'd cry my eyes out.
……栗志江さんをそう評価する生徒もいた。うちのクラス、あるあるの鮮度にやたら厳しい人が多いし……
...There were students who evaluated Kurishie like that. Our class has too many people who are overly critical about the freshness of relatable topics...
なんでそんな厳しいんじゃ。お笑い係とかあるタイプ？
Why are they so harsh? Is it the type of class that has a comedy rep?
私の発見は……面白くもなんともなかった
My discoveries... were not interesting at all.
え、でもさ、こういうさ、あるある系をさ、なんかYouTubeショートでさ、知る、知るとかじゃなくてさ、自分で発見してるのすごいよ！自分で発見してるのすごいのじゃ！
But wait, discovering these relatable tropes on your own, instead of just finding out about them from YouTube Shorts, is actually amazing! It's really impressive!
自分が鈍かった……周回遅れなんだって、最近、やっと気づきました
"I was slow... I was late to the party." I only recently finally realized it.
そんな周回遅れとか寂しいこと言わないでよ！
Don't say sad things like being late to the party!
それなのに自分が初めて見つけたように はしゃいで、披露して……
Even so, I was so excited, showing it off like I was the first to find it...
いいのじゃ、別に。うん。いいけどなあ。
That's fine! Yeah, it's totally fine.
今日も、ご学友と遊ぶなんて滅多に無くて、気持ちが高ぶってしまいました。
Even today, getting to hang out with a classmate is so rare for me that I got overly excited.
ごめんね、帰るボタン押して、ごめんね、帰るボタン押して。
Sorry for clicking the return button, sorry for clicking the return button.
それで……手垢のついた、つまらないことばかり言ってしまった。
And so... I ended up saying nothing but trite, boring things.
栗志江さん……
Kurishi-san...
もれもそうだよ！ もれもだよ！
Me too! Me too!
わしも自分のこと一人称「もれ」だけど、大丈夫なのじゃ。
I also refer to myself as "More," but it's totally fine.
わしも一人称「もれ」なのじゃ！ 終わってるのじゃ！ インターネットドパウッパなのじゃ！
My first-person pronoun is "More" too! I'm doomed! My brain is fried from the internet!
自分も、そういうことあったよ。
I've had times like that, too.
え？ めらおさんが？
Eh? You too, Merao-san?
……子供の時、セミは地面に落ちてても急に鳴くヤツもいるって気づいたんだ。
When I was a kid, I realized some cicadas on the ground would suddenly start buzzing.
当時は大発見だと思ってた。
I thought it was a major discovery back then.
でも友達に「知ってる」って笑われてさ。
But my friends laughed and said, "Duh, we know."
悲しいのじゃ。そう、セミファイナル。セミファイナルのことなのじゃ。
That's so sad. Yeah, the "cicada final." She's talking about the "cicada final."
悔しくて……「〇〇あるある」系のショートをひたすら見て勉強した。
I was so frustrated... I watched "Relatable things" shorts non-stop to study up.
サラマンダーあるあるを見てるのじゃ！ サラマンダーあるあるのショートも見て！
She's watching Salamander relatability videos! Watch those Salamander ones too!
それは、熱心ですね。
That's quite dedicated of you.
最初は楽しいけど、何個も見てるとよく擦られるネタがわかってきて……
It's fun at first, but after watching a bunch, you start to notice the overused tropes...
「このネタ、流行ってるやつの真似じゃん」みたいなのも見えてきて……
and you begin to see things like, "Oh, this is just copying a trending meme..."
ねぇ、そういうこと言うな。めらお、お前はユーチューバーになれ！
Hey, don't say that! Merao, you should become a YouTuber!
お前はユーチューバーにするのじゃ。もう「流行ってるやつの真似じゃん」とか分かってきたら……
You're going to be a YouTuber. Once you start noticing things like "it's just a copy of a trend"...
おぬしが動画を出すフェーズなのじゃ。もう視聴者のフェーズにいないのじゃ、動画を作るのじゃ！
you're ready to start posting videos. You're no longer just a viewer, you need to make them!
そのうちネットじゃ、何を見ても既視感しかなくなってきて……
Eventually, everything you see on the internet starts giving you deja vu...
おぬしが動画を作るのじゃ……！
You must create the videos...!
めらおさん……？
Merao-san...?
おかげで使い古された表現には詳しくなったけど、今度は怖くなった。
Thanks to that, I became an expert on cliché expressions, but then I got scared.
「自分の言った感想や意見が、手垢のついた話だったらどうしよう」って。
Thinking, "What if my own thoughts and opinions are just trite platitudes?"
それらは周りが意地悪すぎるのじゃ！ それらは周りが意地悪すぎるのじゃ！
That's just because the people around you are too mean! That's just them being mean!
いいじゃん別に、あるある言ったってね！
Who cares if you talk about relatable things? It's fine!
それで、映画の感想も明確に言ってはくれなかったんですね。
I see, so that's why you wouldn't give me a clear opinion on the movie.
確かに、めらお映画の感想をはっきり言ってなかった。
True, Merao didn't really say what he thought of the movie.
だから……栗志江さんにはめらおみたいに気にしすぎないでほしいんだ。
So... I don't want you to overthink it like I did, Kurishi-san.
確かに、もう誰かが見つけたことかもしれない。けど、栗志江さんが自分で発見したんでしょう？
True, someone else might have already found it. But you discovered it yourself, right?
それは「つまらないこと」なんかじゃないよ。
That doesn't make it "boring" at all.
……お気遣い、ありがとうございます。
...Thank you for being so considerate.
そう言っていただけるだけでも、嬉しいです。
Just hearing you say that makes me happy.
お似合いじゃない？ めらおと。
Aren't they a great match? Her and Merao.
こんな……それこそ、どこかで聞いたような慰めの言葉じゃ届かない。
These... predictable comforting words, like something heard somewhere before, won't reach her.
昔からそうだ。他人と被ることに怯えてたけど、結局楽だから、他人と同じようなことをして……
I've always been like this. Terrified of copying others, yet doing the exact same because it's easier...
ああ、もう！ ごめん、ちょっと待ってて！
Ah, jeez! Sorry, wait here a second!
めらお、どこか行っちゃった。お似合いなのじゃ、いいカップル。
Merao ran off somewhere. They look so good together, what a nice couple.
へっ？
Huh?
どうした？ めらおどうした？
What's wrong? What is Merao doing?
……公園の入り口にあった、屋台の？
...From the stall by the park entrance?
うん。あの屋台は年中かき氷を売ってる狂った店だから。
Yeah. That stall is a crazy place that sells shaved ice all year round.
狂った店きた！ 狂った店きた、狂った店。
"Crazy place," there it is! "Crazy place," she said it.
どうして急に？
Why so suddenly?
かき氷のシロップはどれも同じ味だってのは、知ってる……知ってるつもりだった。
I know... or rather, I thought I knew that all shaved ice syrups taste the same.
でもそれは、漫画とかネットで見て知った気になってるだけなんだ。
But that's just because I read it in manga or online and assumed it was true.
確かに、実際食べ比べしたことないのじゃ。
True, we've never actually compared them by eating them.
本当に味が同じなのか、自分で確認したことはない。
I've never actually confirmed for myself if they really taste the same.
だから今、試す！
So right now, I'm going to test it!
男気なのじゃ！ かなり、かなりラブラブメロメロいい感じなんじゃない？ くっついちゃえよ。
So manly! They're getting super lovey-dovey, aren't they? Just hook up already!
ああっ！ そんなペースで……！
Ah! At that pace...!
すっごいペースで食べてる。めらお、やばいペースで食べてるのじゃ。
He's eating so fast. Merao is eating at a crazy pace.
ど、どうですか？
H-How is it?
イチゴ味とメロン味。確かにあまり違いはないかも？
Strawberry and melon. There really might not be much difference.
いや、舌が冷えてわからなくなってきた……
No, my tongue is getting numb from the cold, so I can't tell anymore...
ううっ、寒い！ 歯が痛い！
Ugh, so cold! My teeth hurt!
あおう！
Aow!
大変！上着あるので着てください。
Oh no! I have a jacket, so please wear it.
ありがとう、栗志江さん。
Thank you, Kuriie-san.
いい空気じゃないの？
Isn't that a great atmosphere?
いい空気なのじゃ。
What a nice atmosphere.
ラブラブ男女ですのじゃ。
They are a lovey-dovey couple.
こういう人間が付き合うんじゃろ？
These are the kind of people who should date, right?
私も、何度も違う味のかき氷を食べるうちに違和感を覚えたので、食べ比べをしたんですが……
I, too, noticed something was off while eating shaved ice of different flavors multiple times, so I compared them...
ちゃんとゆっくり、温かいお茶を飲みながらやったんですから。早食いはダメですよ！
Because I did it slowly while drinking warm tea. Eating fast is no good!
すごい、この子試したんだね。
Wow, she actually tested it.
自力で気づくのもすごいし、食べ比べて検証するのもすごいな。
Noticing it on her own is amazing, and verifying it by comparing is also amazing.
栗志江さん、全然浅くもつまらなくもないよ。むしろすごいよ……
Kuriie-san, you're not shallow or boring at all. Rather, you're amazing...
ええ、恋の予感。
Ooh, a premonition of love.
そ、そうですか？
I-Is that so?
うん！……ああ、くち冷たい……
Yeah! ...Ah, my mouth is cold...
台無しなのじゃ。
You ruined the moment.
めらおは、大きく口を開けて、冷気を口から逃がそうとした。
Merao opened his mouth wide, trying to let the cold air escape.
ふ、ふふ……っ
He-Hehe...
え？
Huh?
あ、スチルきた。スチル。
Ah, a CG! A CG.
ごめんなさい！でも……あはははっ！
I'm sorry! But... Ahahaha!
めらおさん、舌が真緑！
Merao-san, your tongue is completely green!
おおー、いい空気ですのじゃ。
Ooh, what a nice atmosphere.
あはははは……っ
Ahahaha...
（かき氷のメロン味で舌の色が……）
(My tongue turned green from the melon-flavored shaved ice...)
（またベタなことしちゃったな）
(I did something cliché again.)
（まあ……でも……）
(Well... but...)
（初めて栗志江さんの満面の笑みが見れたし、いいか……）
(It's fine, since I got to see Kuriie-san's full smile for the first time...)
ええ、いい話。
Ooh, a nice story.
いい話。
A nice story.
チューはしてないのじゃ？
They didn't kiss?
そういうのは早いのじゃ？
Is it too early for that?
今日だるかったー。
Today was so tiring.
早く帰ろ〜。
Let's go home early.
今日は何もないし、帰ろうかな。
Nothing's happening today, so I guess I'll go home.
お疲れ様です。
Good job today.
栗志江さん！
Kuriie-san!
（あの日以降、めらおは前よりも栗志江さんと話すようになっていた）
(Since that day, Merao had been talking to Kuriie-san more than before.)
その、これから予定ありますか？部活とか、塾とか。
Um, do you have plans after this? Like club activities or cram school?
え、なんか、すごっ。すごい仲良し！
Oh, wow, they're really close!
すごい仲良しなのじゃ！
They're really close!
まだ付き合ってないの？
They're still not dating?
まだ付き合ってないのじゃ？
ううん。ないよ。
Nope, none.
あ、あの……よ、よかったら……タピオカ屋さんに行きませんか！
U-Um... i-if you'd like... would you like to go to a boba shop!
あー、やっぱね。流行ってる、流行ってたやつね。回収したいよね。
Ah, I knew it. The trendy one. You want to get that event.
デートのお誘いですのじゃ！
It's a date invitation!
タピオカ？
Boba?
はい。私……一人で行った経験はあるのですが……
Yes. I... have been there alone before, but...
「友達とは行ったことない」言ったら、「友達いない」であれかな？悲しくさせちゃうかな？
If she says "I've never been with a friend", that means "I have no friends", so... will it make her sad?
クラスメイトとは行ったことない。クラスメイトとは行ったことないから、とか？
I'll choose "Haven't you been with classmates?". Like, "Have you never been with a classmate?" or something?
クラスメイト……じゃなくて！友達と行きたいんです！
Not... classmates! I want to go with a friend!
も、モテですか！？
Is this... popularity?!
わしなのじゃ？
Am I the one?
うん、もちろん！だけど……
Yeah, of course! But...
友達ならもうちょっと砕けた感じでもいいんじゃない？
If we're friends, shouldn't you speak more casually?
あ……口調、ですか？すみません。この喋り方、癖で……
Ah... my tone? I'm sorry. This way of speaking is a habit...
でも……そうですね。
But... you're right.
一緒に行こ、めらお！
Let's go together, Merao!
ええ、なんか、いい空気！
Ooh, what a nice atmosphere!
いい空気なのじゃ！
What a nice atmosphere!
のじゃ！てあカノ。て垢のついたことしか言わない彼女。
No ja! Teakano. "The girl who only says cliché things".
エンディング５「ひとりじゃわからないこと」
Ending 5: "What I Can't Understand Alone".
いい話なのじゃー！
It's such a nice story!
いい話なのじゃ。
It's a nice story.
エンディング５回収しましたのじゃ。
We got Ending 5.
じゃあ、他のエンディングも回収していくか。
Now, let's go get the other endings too.
他のエンディングも回収していきますのじゃ。
Let's go retrieve the other endings.
チャプター１「待ち合わせ」
Chapter 1: "Meeting Up".
帰るタイミングによって変わるらしい。
Apparently it changes depending on when we go home.
から、一旦この一番最初の、栗志江モカさんの、あのインフルのときの夢で帰ろう。
So, let's first go home during Kuriie Moka's "dream when she had influenza".
インフルのときの夢で帰ろう。
Let's go home during the influenza dream.
即帰宅する。
Go home immediately.
「インフルエンザの時の夢」みたいですね！
"It's like a dream when you have influenza!"
即帰宅する感じ悪くない？でもまあ、回収のためじゃからな。
Isn't it bad to go home immediately? But well, it's to retrieve the ending.
右上に「帰る」ボタンがあり。
There is a "Go Home" button on the top right.
インフルエンザの時の夢。帰る！
A dream when you have influenza. Go home!
いやじゃ。
No way.
え、辛辣…辛辣のじゃ。今時インフルエンザの時の夢って面白いと思ってるのかな。
Wow, harsh... How harsh. "Is he thinking dreams you have when you have the flu are interesting nowadays?"
急激に帰りたくなってきた。適当に理由つけよう…
"I suddenly want to go home. I'll make up some excuse..."
メラお、嫌な奴！メラお、ガチで嫌な奴！
Merao is such an annoying guy! Merao is seriously an annoying guy!
あ、ごめん！今日用事あったんだった。来るな！最初から言え！
"Ah, sorry! I actually had plans today." Don't even come! Tell me that from the start!
栗志江さんごめん、帰らないと。
"Krishie-san, sorry, I have to go home."
まあ、そうなんですか？映画のチケット代は……
"Oh, really? What about the movie ticket..."
自分が悪いし、お金いらないよ、よかったら観てきて！じゃあ！
"It's my fault, so I don't need the money. Enjoy the movie if you like! Bye!"
嫌な奴。なんか苦しい。切なくなってきたのじゃ。辛い。うーん。
Such an annoying guy. It's kind of painful. It's getting sad. So painful. Hmm.
モカ…最低なのじゃ。
Moka... This is the worst.
どうだった？日曜に栗志江さんと遊んだんでしょ？うん、まあ。
"How did it go? You hung out with Krishie-san on Sunday, right?" "Yeah, well..."
栗志江さんと！？何話したんだよ、メラお！いや、そんなに……
"With Krishie-san?! What did you talk about, Merao?!" "No, not much..."
何だよそれ、栗志江さんは何か言ってた？駅のオブジェをインフルの時に見る夢に例えてた。
"What's that about? Did Krishie-san say anything?" "She compared the station sculpture to 'a dream you have when you have the flu'."
あー……ねぇ、このタイミングで栗志江さん入ってきたらどうするのじゃ。
Ah... Hey, what would we do if Krishie-san walked in right now?
栗志江さんってそういうところあるよね。『今それ？』みたいな話を、面白い感じで言ってくるの。
Krishie-san is kind of like that. "She brings up things that make you go 'Are you talking about that now?' as if it's funny."
『行けたら行く』は結局来ない、とか、二日目のカレーの方が美味しい、とか……
"Like 'I'll go if I can' means they won't come, or 'Curry on the second day tastes better'..."
え、何それ！
"Whoa, what's that?!"
やばー、一周目すぎるっしょ！
"That's crazy! She's way too basic!"
いくら顔が良くても、つまんねー女は性格悪いとかよりしんどい……
"No matter how pretty she is, a boring girl is worse than one with a bad personality..."
そんなことないのじゃ！そんなことないのじゃ！つまんない、性格悪い女の方が嫌なのじゃ！
That's not true! That's not true! I'd hate a boring, bad-tempered woman more!
今時ネットとか賞レースで一般人もお笑いのリテラシー上がってるんだからさ。もう少し何というか……
"With the internet and comedy awards, even regular people have high comedy standards nowadays. So, how do I put it..."
何？あ、栗志江さん入ってきたじゃん。絶対入ってきたじゃん。
What? Ah, Krishie-san entered, didn't she? She definitely did.
あ、おはよう、栗志江さん。
"Ah... Good morning, Krishie-san."
ねぇ、嫌だ！クラス通いたくないのじゃ！転校するのじゃ！
No, I hate this! I don't want to go to this class! I'm transferring!
おはようございます。
"...Good morning."
栗志江さんは会釈をすると、足早に離れていった。
Krishie-san bowed slightly and quickly walked away.
それが、栗志江さんとまともに会話した最後の機会だった……
That was the last opportunity I had to properly talk with Krishie-san...
ねえ、嫌だクラス！
No, I hate this class!
不登校になるのじゃ。行かないのじゃ。こんな学校行かないのじゃ。エンディング1『疎遠』。切ないのじゃー。
I'll stop going to school. I'm not going. I won't go to a school like this. Ending 1: Estranged. So sad.
子供って悪気なくこういうことするよね。でもそれって悪意なのじゃ。
Kids do these things without meaning any harm. But that itself is malice.
嫌な学校。心が痛いのじゃ。
I hate school. My heart hurts.
もう帰りたくなくなってきた。もう帰りたくない。次は映画館で帰らなきゃいけないのじゃ。次は私、映画館で帰らなきゃいけない。苦しいのじゃ。
I don't want to go home anymore. I don't want to go home. Next time I have to go home from the movie theater. Next time I have to go home from the movie theater. It's painful.
映画楽しみですのじゃ。のじゃ。あーこんな良い子なのに。こんな良い子なのに帰らなきゃいけない。こんな良い子なのに。
I'm looking forward to the movie, noja. Noja. Ah, even though she's such a good girl. Even though she's such a good girl, I have to go home. Even though she's such a good girl.
感動、私、疑問？疑問があるんですって。
"Emotional," "I," "Question?" She says she has a question.
全米が泣いたという宣伝文句、本当だと思いますか……？そうだよね、全米が泣いたって本当に泣いたか分からないよね。
"Do you think the tagline 'The whole nation cried' is true...?" That's right! You don't know if they really cried.
私だって、あの唐揚げの金賞受賞って本当に、全部の唐揚げが金賞になってるなって思うのじゃ。そういうことってあるのじゃ。うん。
Even for me, I think those Karaage gold award winners... really, does every single Karaage win a gold award? These things happen. Yeah.
観客の皆さんが泣いているか、全てチェックするのは無理ですよね？確かに。栗志江さん真剣だ。
"It's impossible to check if every audience member is crying, right?" True. Krishie-san is so serious.
あー。最初に帰る、と回収すればよかった。最初に帰ればよかった。
Ah... I should have chosen "go home" first to collect it. I should have gone home first.
いたた……いたたた……
"Ow... Ouch, ouch..."
大丈夫ですか？
"Are you okay?"
いや、お腹が……ツッ……アー……いっ……いや、これマジで……ツッ……やばい、マジで……仮病なのじゃ！
"No, my stomach... Ah, this is seriously bad, seriously..." It's a fake illness!
大変！無理せず、今日は帰りましょう。うん、本当にごめんね。チケット代はいらないから。
"Oh dear! Please don't overdo it, let's go home today." "Yeah, I'm really sorry. You don't have to pay for the ticket."
それじゃあ。はい、お気をつけて。
"Well then." "Yes, please take care."
あー。順番間違えたのじゃ。おはよう。おはよう。おはよー。
Ah... I got the order wrong. "Good morning." "Good morning." "Morning."
あ、栗志江さん。クラスの他の女子と話しているようだ。
"Ah, Krishie-san." (She seems to be talking to another girl in class.)
それでね。まあ、そうなんですね。そうなのー。でさー。うふふ、そうなんですね。
"So, you see." "Oh, is that so?" "Yeah. And then..." "Haha, I see."
あれ？栗志江さん……全然自分の話してないな。
"Huh? Krishie-san..." She doesn't talk about herself at all.
あの日以来、栗志江さんは会話の時、いつも微笑みで相手を肯定していた。うわ、社会性を覚えちゃったんだ。社会性を覚えちゃって。嫌なのじゃ。
"Since that day, whenever Krishie-san talked, she always smiled and agreed with the other person." Wow, she learned social survival skills. She learned social skills... I hate this.
あー、自分の思っていることが素直に言える環境がなくなっちゃったのじゃ
Ah, the environment where she could speak her mind freely has vanished...
しかし、自分から話を切り出したり、周りと違う意見を言うことは二度となかった...
However, she never again initiated conversation or expressed a differing opinion...
エンディング2、栗志江さんは語らない
Ending 2: "Kurishie-san doesn't speak."
切ないのじゃ、うわ
How painful... Whoa.
なんかノベルゲー初めてじゃからさー
Since this is my first visual novel...
わしさ、ノベルゲーやったことなかったからさ、お作法知らなかったけどさ
I've never played a visual novel before, so I didn't know the proper way to play...
もしかしてさ、こういうノベルゲーってさ
But maybe, in visual novels like this...
バッドエンドを最初に回収して、いいエンドにするべきだったの？
you're supposed to collect the bad endings first, and then go for the good ending?
うわー、知らなかった
Wow, I had no idea.
知らなかったのじゃー
I didn't know that!
じゃあ、エンディング4も見るか
Well, let's see Ending 4 as well.
切ないのじゃー
How painful...
うー、つらいのじゃ。公園にきたのじゃ。
Oof, this is tough. We've come to the park...
ガキンチョが、ドパパッパが、ほら、ドパパッパが生意気なことを言うエンディング
The brats... the kids... look, the ending where they say cheeky things.
うん、セイレーンを... 書いて書いて、何か面白いもの書いてよ
Yeah, a siren... "draw, draw, draw something funny."
いや、急に言われても。期待されてる、期待されてる！
"Even if you ask me so suddenly..." They're expecting it, they're expecting it!
えっと、ムキムキ猫型ロボ
Let's see, "Buff cat-like robot"...
ダメだって。何周しても、小学生は辛辣ですのじゃ。
They say it's no good. No matter how many loops, elementary schoolers are harsh.
あれ、マジか...
Wait, really?
笑ってる！栗志江さん笑ってくれてありがとう！
She's laughing! Kurishie-san, thank you for laughing!
失礼な！黙れ！黙れ！いっしゅうめとか言うな！
How rude! Shut up! Shut up! Don't say "first week"!
のじゃ！大笑いしてる
Yes! She was cracking up.
のじゃ
Indeed.
え、このあと帰るの辛くない？
Wait, going home after this is going to be so painful, isn't it?
この流れで帰るのやばくない？この流れで帰るのじゃ
Leaving with this vibe is bad, isn't it? We're going home with this vibe...
この流れで？この流れで帰る選択するの？
With this vibe? We're choosing to go home with this vibe?
無理ですのじゃー
No way!
帰るけど、酷いのじゃ
We are going home, but this is cruel.
メラおは帰った
"Merao went home."
人の心とかないんか？
Does he not have a human heart?
栗志江さんは変わらない笑顔で、手を振っていた
"Kurishie-san waved with her usual smile."
バケモノなのじゃ、サラマンダーのほうがもうちょい心あるのじゃ
Is he a monster? Even a salamander has more heart than him!
おはよう。おはよう。
Morning. Morning.
栗志江さんいないな、いつも早いのに
Kurishie-san isn't here, even though she's usually early...
休みだって。うわ、絶対にメラおのせいじゃ！
She's absent. Ugh, this is absolutely Merao's fault!
そうかじゃねえよ！女の子泣かせんな！
Don't just say "I see"! Don't make a girl cry!
次の日
The next day...
体調不良で欠席だそうだ。ねえー、メラおー！
"Absent due to poor health." Come on, Merao!
え...
Huh...
なんか途中まで心開いてさ、いける予感出してさ、やっぱ無理って拒絶するの、一番良くないのじゃ。次の日――
Opening up halfway and giving hope, then rejecting her in the end is the absolute worst thing to do. Next day—
栗志江は今日も欠席か。誰か家近い奴いるか？
Kurishie is absent today too, huh? Is there anyone who lives near her?
うーーん
Hmm...
次の日、栗志江さんは学校に来た
The next day, Kurishie-san came to school.
みんな心配していたし、栗志江さんも穏やかにそれに答えていた
Everyone was worried, and Kurishie-san responded to them calmly.
ただ、それからの栗志江さんは、あの日の発剌さを永久に失っていた
However, ever since then, Kurishie-san had permanently lost her liveliness...
ねえー！何しとんのー！
Hey! What have you done!?
子供にバカにされたあと、栗志江さんは目に見えて落ち込んでいたじゃないか
After being made fun of by the kids, Kurishie-san was visibly depressed, wasn't she?
あの時帰らなければ、違う結末があったのだろうか
If I hadn't gone home back then, would there have been a different outcome...?
エンディング4、分岐点
Ending 4: "Branching Point"
一番良くないタイミングで帰っちゃった
We went home at the absolute worst possible timing.
切ないのじゃー
How painful...
なんか...
Somehow...
順番があったな。順番があったな。
There was an order. There was an order.
エンディング全部回収しましたのじゃ
I collected all of the endings.
したけど、したけど...
I did, but... I did, but...
エンディング回収ってこんな辛い作業なんだ。知らなかった。
Collecting endings is such a painful task. I didn't know.
もう一回ハッピーエンド見るか？もう一回ハッピーエンド見るか？
Should I look at the happy end one more time? Should I look at it again??
よし
Alright.
もう一回、最後の、あの、嬉しいとこ見よう
Let's look at the last happy part one more time.
嬉しいとこ見て、帰るを選択して
Let's watch the happy part, select "go home"...
いや、帰るを選択して、帰らないか
No, select "go home"... wait, "don't go home".
はい、笑ってる！
Yes, she's laughing!
笑ってる
They're laughing.
はーい
Okay.
うん
Mm-hmm.
変じゃないよ。変じゃないのじゃ。
It's not weird. It's not weird at all.
大丈夫、帰らない、帰らない！
It's okay, we're not going home!
帰らないのじゃ！
We're absolutely not going home!
は、はいっ
Y-Yes...
帰らないのじゃーー！
We're not going home!
心痛くなってからのじゃ。
This is where it starts to hurt...
栗志江さんって、中学までどんな感じだったの？
Kurishie-san, what was middle school like for you?
うーん、そりゃ全寮制だったらね、知識も偏りますよ。
Well, if you were at a boarding school, your knowledge would definitely be biased.
帰国子女ですと。日本に帰って来たばかり。
So she's a returnee who just came back to Japan.
うーん、校則も厳しくて、そうだよね。
Yeah, and the rules were really strict, I see...
それでした、日本に帰ることになってさ、父を説得してさ、
So she returned to Japan, persuaded her dad,
超説得してさ、だって箱入り娘なわけでしょ？
persuaded him super hard—since she's a sheltered girl, right?
父を説得して公立高校に進学した結果、
And after persuading her father and entering a public high school...
さっきみたいに嫌な陰口言われるんでしょ？
she gets nasty rumors spread about her?
泣いちゃうけどね！
I would totally cry!
楽しみにしてた世界が、実はすごい意地悪なものでしたって。
To find out the world you looked forward to is actually so cruel.
大号泣じゃけど、絶望じゃけど。世界が嫌になっちゃうけど。ねえ？
I'd sob my eyes out, lose all hope. It'd make me hate the world. Right?
ねえ、父に意見とかあんましなさそうなのにね。嫌な話なのじゃ。
And she doesn't seem like the type to stand up to her dad. This is so sad.
やっぱ私立に行くのじゃ。お嬢様はね、お嬢様はお嬢様と一緒にいた方が多分いい。
Honestly, she should go to a private school. Rich girls should probably stick together.
スマホも解禁されて、普通の学生生活が送れるようになった、嬉しいのじゃ。
Her phone was unbanned, and she can finally live a normal life. How nice.
うん、行きたいイベントに行って、楽しんでる、いい話なのじゃ。
Mm, she's going to events and enjoying herself. It's a heartwarming story.
初めて知ることがたくさん。初めて知った嬉しかったことを、わしに教えてくれたんでしょ？いい子じゃんか！
So many firsts. And she's sharing the happy things she learned with me, right? What a sweet girl!
いい子なのじゃ。
She's such a good girl.
かき氷シロップね。わしがかき氷買ってきてあげるから。
Shaved ice syrup, huh. I'll go buy you some shaved ice!
毎日新しい発見があって楽しかった。いいことじゃ、いいことなのじゃ。
Having new discoveries every day and enjoying it... That's wonderful.
そんなことないよーー！
That is absolutely not true!
嫌な、嫌な女子、嫌な女子、嫌な女子！
Ugh, nasty girls. Nasty girls. Nasty girls!
つまんないとか言わない！
Don't call her boring!
知る、知ってる話しかないとか言わない！厳しいのじゃ！
Don't say she only talks about things you already know! How harsh!
いいだろ別に！
So what! Who cares!
てか何かこっちの方が社会性ないのじゃ。こっちの方が社会性ないのじゃ。
Honestly, they are the ones who lack social skills.
人間社会なんてさ、あ、それ知ってるな、っていう話をさ、
Human society is all about talking about things everyone knows...
人間社会のコミュニケーションってさ、敵意がないことを示すためにする会話じゃろ？
Daily communication is just meant to show you have no hostility, right?
別にその会話に、そんな体験価値を見出そうとしてないのじゃ、人間って。
Humans aren't trying to find some deep, intellectual value in small talk.
人間はただ、いや、この群れに属するために私は敵意がないことを証明しますよ、てのをアピールするためだけの手段として
It's just a tool to show, "I'm friendly, so please let me belong to this herd."
こういうコミュニケーションをとってるから、
That's why we have these kind of conversations.
なんかそれを肯定しない方が社会性ないのじゃ。そういうもんのじゃ。
So failing to appreciate that actually shows a lack of social skills. That's just how it is.
やばじゃないのじゃ。厳しいのじゃ。
She's not weird. They are just being too harsh.
最悪なのじゃ。嫌な、嫌なクラス、嫌なクラス。
That's the worst. What a horrible, horrible class.
そんなことないよ！
That's not true!
That is not true!
やっぱ人には人の初めてがあるから、人には人の初めてがあるから、肯定しなきゃ！
Everyone has their own 'first time' for everything, so you have to support that!
ねえ、それで遊んでくれたわけでしょう。嬉しいでしょう？
But you did hang out with them today. Isn't that something to be happy about?
それがコミュニケーションですのじゃ。それも含めて許容するのがコミュニケーションですのじゃ。
But that is what communication is. Accepting all of that is what communication is.
こっち選んだからこっち選んでみるか。
I chose this before, so let's try selecting this one.
本当だような。誰が教えてくれるのじゃ、コミュニケーションって。体当たりで知っていくしかないのじゃ。
Exactly. Who even teaches you communication anyway? You just have to learn by trial and error.
あるある系はね、鉄板なのじゃ。全人類に刺さるからね。やり得なのじゃ、やり得なのじゃ。だからわしも初配信であるあるを入れたのじゃ。
Relatable content is a solid standard. It hits home for everyone. It's always a win. That's why I did it in my first stream too.
そうなんじゃ。わかってくる。ねえ、そんなこと言わないで。
Yeah, you do. Hey, don't say that.
そのうちネットじゃ、何を見ても、既視感しかなくなってきて……
Before long, looking at anything on the internet just gave me deja vu...
メラおさん……？
Merao-san...?
おかげで使い古された表現には詳しくなったけど、今度は怖くなった
Thanks to that, I became well-versed in worn-out expressions, but then it became scary.
メラおも怯えてますよと
"Merao is also scared," it says.
そうなのだじゃ
I see.
お前は俺だ。俺はお前なのだじゃ。うーむ。
"You are me, and I am you." Hmm.
「自分の言った感想や意見が、手垢のついた話だったらどうしよう」って
"What if my own thoughts and opinions are just clichéd?"
あ、もう怯えることないと思うけどな。環境が悪い。
Ah, I don't think there's any need to be scared anymore. The environment is bad.
てか、なんかそれで不安になるような環境ならもう、
I mean, if the environment makes you feel anxious like that,
パパに言って、転校させてもらおう。
tell your papa and have him let you transfer schools.
学校が悪いのだじゃ。いじわるすぎますのだじゃ。うむ。
The school is bad. They are way too mean. Yeah.
それで、映画の感想も、明確に言ってはくれなかったんですね
So that's why you didn't give me a clear opinion on the movie either.
だって、モカもだけどさ、クリシェもだけどのさ、
But, same for Moka and Cliche...
あの、メラおは割と被害者だよね。
Merao is pretty much the victim here, right?
メラおもそれで感想言えなくなっちゃったんでしょ？
That's why Merao couldn't say his opinion either, right?
もう悪じゃん。学校が悪なのだじゃ。
That's just evil. The school is the evil one.
学校が悪なのだじゃ。転校しよう。
The school is evil. Let's transfer schools.
だから……栗志さんにはメラおみたいに気にしすぎないでほしいんだ
So... I don't want you to worry about it too much like I do, Kurishi-san.
確かにもう誰かが見つけたことかもしれない。けど、栗志さんが自分で発見したんでしょ？
It's true that someone else might have already found it. But you discovered it yourself, right?
それはすごいことだよ。尊いことなのだじゃ。つまらなくないのだじゃ。
That's an amazing thing. It's precious. It's not boring at all.
……お気遣い、ありがとうございます
...Thank you for your concern.
（気を使わせてるのは、こっちだ）
(I'm the one who's making her worry.)
ああ、もう！ メラお、かき氷持ってくる。かき氷持って行くよ！
Ah, jeez! Merao is bringing shaved ice. I'm bringing shaved ice!
よし。
Alright.
じゃじゃーん。かき氷のじゃ、狂ったかき氷のじゃ。
Ta-da! Shaved ice, the crazy shaved ice.
……公園の入り口にあった、屋台の？
...From the stand near the park entrance?
うん。あの屋台は年中かき氷を売ってる狂った店だから
Yeah. That stand is a crazy shop that sells shaved ice all year round, so...
どうして急に？
Why so suddenly?
かき氷のシロップはどれも同じ味だっていうのは、知ってる……知ってるつもりだった
I know that all shaved ice syrups taste the same... Or at least, I thought I did.
実際試さないとわかんないよね。
You won't know until you actually try it, right?
超冷たい。つめ、つめ、つむむ、メラ。つむむ、メラ！
Super cold. Co- co- cold- Mera. Cold, Mera!
でも、それは漫画とかネットで見て知った気になってるだけなんだ
But that's just because I feel like I know it from manga or the internet.
試してみた。かき氷本当に違う味か試してみたっていう動画を出すのだじゃ。
I tried it. I'll put out a video testing if shaved ice really has different tastes.
本当に味が同じなのか、自分で確認したことはない
I've never confirmed for myself whether they really taste the same.
だから今、試す！
So now, I will test it!
ああっ！ そんなペースで……！
Ah! At that pace...!
びっくりしてる。「そんなペースで食べるんじゃないよ」と。
She's surprised. Like, "Don't eat at that pace!"
ど、どうですか？
H-How is it?
イチゴ味とメロン味。確かにあまり違いはないかも？
Strawberry and melon. Indeed, there might not be much difference?
いや、舌が冷えてわからなくなってきた……まぬけなのだじゃ！
"No, my tongue went cold and I can't tell anymore..." What a dummy!
歯が痛いのだじゃ！
My teeth hurt!
ううっ、寒い！ 歯が痛い！
Ugh, cold! My teeth hurt!
大変！ 上着あるので着てください。てぇてぇ、ほっこりじゃの。お似合いじゃの。
Oh no! "I have a jacket, so please wear it." How wholesome. They look good together.
大変！ 上着あるので着てください
Oh no! I have a jacket, so please wear it.
ありがとう、栗志さん
Thank you, Kurishi-san.
私も、何度も違う味のかき氷を食べるうちに違和感を覚えたので、食べ比べをしたんですが……
I also felt something was off while eating shaved ice of different flavors, so I compared them, but...
実は、さむむ、今ここでメラお食べ比べしましたが、栗志さんも食べ比べをしています。
Actually, Merao just did a taste comparison here, but Kurishi-san has also done one.
栗志さん行動派なのだじゃ。あるあるを見てね、食べ比べまで実際やっちゃってみよう。
Kurishi-san is a woman of action. Seeing a common trope, she actually tried comparing them.
「本当にどうなのかな」って疑問を持つ人あんまりいないのだじゃ。
There aren't many people who actually wonder "I wonder how it really is."
ショートで流れてきたことは「ふーん」ってその場で忘れるのだじゃ、基本的には。
Usually, you just go "huh" at things that pop up on Shorts and forget about it on the spot.
試すまで行くのは相当な。そこまで言ったらもう趣味でいいのだじゃ。
Going as far as testing it is quite something. At that point, it can just be a hobby.
栗志さん、全然浅くもつまらなくもないよ。むしろすごいよ……
Kurishi-san, that's not shallow or boring at all. Indeed, it's amazing...
そ、そうですか？
I-Is that so?
うん！ ……ああ、口冷たい。
Yeah! ...Ah, my mouth is cold.
ふ、ふふ……っ
He, hehe...
そして、いい笑顔！
And then, what a great smile!
ごめんなさい！ でも……
I'm sorry! But...
あはははっ！
Ahahaha!
メラおさん、舌が真緑！
Merao-san, your tongue is completely green!
やったのだじゃ！ いいお話！ いいお話でしたのだじゃ。
We did it! What a nice story! That was a really nice story.
（またベタなことしちゃったな。まあ……でも……）
(I ended up doing something cliché again. Well... but...)
（初めて栗志さんの満面の笑みが見れたし、いいか……）
(I got to see Kurishi-san's full smile for the first time, so I guess it's fine...)
いいお話ですのだじゃー！
It's a really nice story!
やっぱ、ハッピーエンド、じゃよな。
After all, a happy ending is the best, right?
やっぱハッピーエンドしか、勝たんのだじゃ。
Happy endings always win.
タピオカ行きたいのだじゃ。
I want to go get boba.
誘ってきた！ 好感度爆上がり！ 純愛！
She invited him! Affection points are skyrocketing! Pure love!
タピオカ屋さんに行きませんか？
Would you like to go to a boba shop?
友達とは行ったことない？
You haven't gone with friends?
友達ならもうちょっと崩した感じでもいいんじゃない？
If we're friends, maybe we can be a bit more casual?
この喋り方、変ですか……？
Is the way I talk weird...?
一緒にいこ、メラお！ 行くのだじゃー！
"Let's go together, Merao!" We're going!
やったー！ ハッピーエンド！
Yay! Happy ending!
てあかの。手垢のついたことしか言わない彼女。
"Teakano." The girl who only speaks in clichés.
Thank You For Playing!
いい笑顔なのだじゃー！
What a great smile!
はぁー、いいお話じゃった。
Haa, that was a really nice story.
いいお話じゃった。
That was a really nice story.
やっぱ、人間には優しくしよう。
After all, let's be kind to humans.
ふふふっ。人間には優しくしよう。
Hehehe. Let's be kind to humans.
ちょっとお話しするために、お部屋変わろうかな。
I think I'll change rooms so we can talk a bit.
お部屋変わりますのだじゃ。
Changing rooms now.
のだじゃーーー！
--da ja!
であカノで遊ぶのじゃ！
Let's play DeaKano!
なんか、もしもさ
Like, what if...
インターネット始めたての頃
back when I first started using the internet...
結構苦労したけど
I had quite a tough time, but...
インターネット、やっぱどこにでも初見さんっているのじゃ？
There are always newcomers everywhere on the internet, right?
どこにでも初見さんっているから
Since there are newcomers everywhere...
ちょっと待って、キノコとタケノコちょっと
Wait a second, let me just...
一旦これ消すか
Let's remove this for now.
一旦これ、争いを生むものは消すのじゃ
For now, let's remove anything that stirs up conflict.
んで、高評価を促すのじゃ
And then let's encourage people to hit the like button.
ちょっと、一旦ね
Just for a moment...
そういえば忘れてたのじゃ
Come to think of it, I completely forgot.
ストーリーを観てて忘れていた
I was so engrossed in the story that I forgot.
忘れてたのじゃ
I totally forgot.
おそろしいのじゃ
How terrifying.
キノコルート見ないのじゃ
I won't be looking at the mushroom route.
もう、配信で触っている以上ね
Since we're playing this on stream, after all...
配信で触ってる以上ね
since we're playing it on stream...
で、どっちなのじゃって？
"So, which one is it?" they ask.
高評価がいますのじゃ
There's the like button.
だめのじゃ
No way.
だめですのじゃ、答えませんのじゃ、沈黙！
No way, I won't answer. Silence!
沈黙なのじゃ
Silence!
黙秘権を行使しますのじゃ
I will exercise my right to remain silent.
のじゃ、怖いから
Because it's scary...
神回避
Perfect dodge!
んで、朝、朝ののじゃイングリッシュでちょうどその話してたから
And since we were just talking about that during this morning's Noja-English,
あの、伏線回収みたいだったのじゃ
it felt like a foreshadowing payoff.
ちょっとやっぱあの、VTuberとして表に出ている
Well, after all, as a VTuber active in public,
あおちりめらとしての見解を出すことは
giving my personal opinion as Aochili Mela...
ちょっと控えますのじゃ
is something I'll refrain from doing.
友達とかと話すときは話すかもしれないけど
I might talk about it when chatting with friends, but...
VTuberとしてね
as a VTuber, you see...
お話ししてしまうとね
if I speak on it,
ちょっと、なかなか、なかなかね
it's quite, you know, quite difficult.
ですのじゃ
Indeed.
面白かった。ノベルゲー初めてだったけど、こういう感じなんじゃな
That was fun. It was my first visual novel game, so this is how they work.
これ、これで覚えちゃダメか？
Wait, I shouldn't use this one as my baseline, right?
基本変えられないか。基本変えられないで、会話の選択肢で分岐してく感じか
Is it basically unchangeable? Like, you can't change the main flow, and it just branches based on dialogue options?
そんな感じな気がしたのじゃ
That's the feeling I got.
でも、やっぱ
But, after all...
帰るって最悪。帰るって最悪なのじゃ
Leaving to go home is the worst. Going home is just the absolute worst.
傷つく
It's so hurtful.
てか誘ったのに、誘って帰るって一番失礼じゃない？
I mean, they invited me! Inviting someone out and then just leaving is the rudest thing ever, right?
なら誘うなよって思わん？
Doesn't it make you think, "Then don't invite me in the first place"?
だって、きっと可愛いなとかさ、可愛いな、で誘ってさ
Because surely they invited me because they thought, "She's cute," or something...
あ、可愛いだけかよ、で帰るのってガチ、カ、クズ、クズ、クズ男すぎない？
And then leaving thinking, "Ah, she's only cute" is seriously... what a scumbag move!
メラ、クズ男すぎない？
Isn't Mela being way too much of a scumbag?
そういうのよくないのじゃ
That's really not good.
自分の決断に責任を持つのじゃ
You have to take responsibility for your own decisions.
ウラシエさん傷ついちゃったよ、だって
"Urashie-san got hurt," they say.
そう。相手の全部を受け止める覚悟で誘わないと
Right. You shouldn't invite someone unless you're ready to accept everything about them.
で、なんかその、全部を受け止められるほどの、なんだろ、関係値とか、知らない子を誘うなという話ではあるな。知らないのに誘っちゃダメなのじゃ
And, well, don't go inviting a stranger unless you have a relationship close enough to accept everything about her. You shouldn't invite someone you don't even know!
ね、可哀想だった
Yeah, she was so pitiful.
のじゃーー！
Nojaaaa!
なんか、最初の方結構きつかったんだよな。自分の黒歴史が...
Like, the beginning was pretty rough for me. My own dark past...
黒歴史というか、なんか、これってワシのことだ！って思っちゃって
Well, not really a dark past, but I found myself thinking, "This is about me!" and...
切なかったけど...
It was painful, but...
だめじゃ
No good.
自分に刺さる、刺さりまくったのじゃ
It hit home. It really stabbed me deep.
こういう時代あったな
I had times like that.
ワシにもこういうことあったな、って思った
I thought, "I went through stuff like that, too."
冷笑って良くない
Cynicism is not good.
人が面白いと思っているものを、小馬鹿にして笑うの良くない
Mocking and laughing at things that others find interesting is really not good.
当たり前です。良くないのじゃ
Of course it's not. It's really bad.
でも、正直若さってある。正直そういう、なんじゃろな、思春期...
But honestly, that's just youth. Honestly, during that kind of, what do you call it, puberty...
中二病とかそういうのって正直通ると思うのじゃ
Honestly, I think everyone goes through a chunibyo phase.
そういう時期ってあるから 誰にでもあるから
Because we all have those times. Everyone does.
その時期を否定することはしないけど
I won't deny that phase of life,
大人になって「あの頃の自分痛かったな」とか
but once you grow up and think, "My past self was so cringe,"
「あれはよくなかったな」って思えてたらオッケーな気がする
or "that wasn't great," I think you're perfectly fine.
思えたらそれはもう成長なのじゃ
If you can think that, then you've already grown.
そういう時期はある
We all go through periods like that.
あるし 思うことはあっても表に出さなきゃいい
Even if you feel that way, it's fine if you don't show it.
逆張り冷笑が別に悪いわけじゃなくて
Being a contrarian cynic isn't inherently bad,
それを人に押し付けたりするからよくないのじゃ
but imposing it on other people is what makes it bad.
心の中で思ってる分には別にいいからな
It's totally fine as long as you keep it to yourself.
冷笑とか逆張りとかって 自分の心を守るためにすることってないかの？
Don't you think cynicism or contrarianism is often to protect your own heart?
それをする事で自分の心を守っている節があると思っているのじゃ
I feel like people do that to shield their own feelings.
スタバとかに自分だけ誘ってもらえなくて 寂しいから武装するみたいな
Like being left out of Starbucks, feeling lonely, so you arm yourself.
そういう予防線を張っていくみたいな
It's like putting up defensive walls.
自分の中で言い訳をしてるみたいな
You're just making excuses to yourself...
「別に興味ないし だから誘われなくていいもん」みたいな
...like, "I didn't care anyway, so it's fine if I wasn't invited."
いうことがわしあったから 反省なのじゃ
I used to do that myself, so I'm reflecting on it.
そう
Exactly.
だから まあ
So, well...
なんじゃろうな
how should I put it?
他人を傷つけない 態度に出さない
Don't hurt others, and don't let it show in your attitude.
1周目の人には優しくする 自分もそういう時期があったのだから
Be kind to beginners. After all, you had that phase too.
自分もそういう時期があったのだから
Because we've all been through that phase.
「いい気づきじゃの わしもその領域にたどり着いたことがあったよ」って
Accept them kindly, like, "That's a good realization. I've been there too."
おぬしらもね 「VTuber初めて見ます」とか そういう
So when you see people saying things like, "It's my first time watching a VTuber,"
初めましてさんはきっと今後いっぱい出会ってくと思うけど 優しくしよう
we'll meet lots of newcomers from now on, so let's be nice to them.
優しくね
Be kind.
「あ、あったあった 自分もそういうことが」
"Ah, yes, I had times like that too."
そしてできるだけ優しく教えてあげるのじゃ
And guide them as gently as you possibly can.
そうすることで優しく教えられた人は次の新人に優しくなる気がする
By doing that, the person you helped will likely be kind to the next newcomer.
優しさの輪なのじゃ
It creates a circle of kindness.
わしも新人じゃよ
I'm a newcomer too!
わしも新人VTuberじゃから優しくしてほしいのじゃ 優しくして
I'm also a rookie VTuber, so please treat me gently. Be nice to me!
ってもうされてる もうすでにされてますのじゃ
Oh wait, you already do. You're already so kind to me.
ありがとうのじゃ
Thank you so much.
そろそろおしまい 予定だしちゃおう
Well, it's about time to finish. Let me show you the schedule.
明日は8時からソピアとあそびたいぜんで遊びますのじゃ
Tomorrow at 8:00 PM, I'll play Clubhouse Games with Sophia.
9日はあそびまわりたいでクイズの企画やりますのじゃ
On the 9th, we'll do a quiz show stream.
10日の19時からはスパゲッティのゲームを フブキ先輩から頂いたゲームなのじゃ
At 7:00 PM on the 10th, I'll play a spaghetti game Fubuki-senpai gave me.
11日はリズム天国がありますのじゃ
On the 11th, we have Rhythm Heaven.
お楽しみに お楽しみに
Look forward to it! Look forward to it!
おしまい
That's all.
じゃあおぬしら また明日の配信で会おうね
Well then, everyone, see you in tomorrow's stream.
挨拶はバイバイのじゃでいきますのじゃ いや さらばじゃだ
Let's do "Bye-bye noja" for the sign-off... Wait, no, it's "Saraba-ja."
挨拶はさらばじゃで行くのじゃ おぬしら
Let's sign off with "Saraba-ja," everyone!
さらばじゃー！
Saraba-ja!
ご視聴感謝なのじゃ！
Thank you for watching!